Heat. Heat.
Heat.
Welcome Living Mana Church family. We
are so happy to be here with you and so
happy that you are here with us. It is
the Sabbath, so we are happy for the
Sabbath and the joy that it brings. So,
please put in the chat where you're
viewing from. And if this is your very
first time worshiping with Living Manage
Church, we want you to put a one in the
chat. I have to say that we are so proud
of our LLC youth. They did an amazing
job last Sabbath. We were blessed. It
was great to be in the seat of a viewer
and be blessed.
>> Yeah,
>> they all did such such a great job.
We're very proud of them.
>> Um and yeah, we're going to have we need
to have some more youth Sabbaths and so
>> we'll be praying.
>> More are coming.
>> Yeah, more are coming. We'll be praying
and planning for that for the next year.
But
>> it is such a blessing. So, yes, please
put in the chat. I see some of you
putting in the chat. I Let's see. Let me
look here because that one went up kind
of quick. I think it was Europe. Okay.
From East Europe, welcome to Living Mana
Church. We have uh Tanzania. Welcome.
Good to see you here. Uh from Barbados.
I'm not really catching first names, but
welcome. So thankful that you are here.
>> Tanzania.
>> Uh yeah, I did Tanzania already. Um
let's see. We have Laura from
Greensville, North Carolina. Welcome. We
have our dear sister Jodie from
Vancouver Island, Canada. We got to come
up there and visit you, Jodie, to
Vancouver. We've been to Vancouver, but
not obviously Vancouver Island.
>> Um, okay. So, yeah, Jody, that's me
inviting us to your to your house. Um,
okay, then. Southern Oregon. Beautiful.
All right. We're very international
today. Praise the Lord. We uh would say
we got South Africa. Good to see you
here. Another Barbados. Go ahead. And
don't worry, South Africa. Uh we were uh
a little bit late jumping on. So you're
actually not late.
>> Oh, you're not late. You're right on
time because what does the enemy try to
do on Sabbath morning? He tries to mess
with our technology. But what does God
do? He fights back and he wins. So we're
here. Yes. All right. We're a very
European church today. All right.
Portugal, welcome. Good to see you here.
Want to visit your country. We've been
to Italy and they say port Portugal is
just as beautiful as Italy. So, we want
to come there, too.
>> Uh, let's see. Anguila. All right. LMOC,
the international church. I love it.
Okay. I skipped I skipped some of our
American spots. Sorry. Grand Rapids,
Michigan.
>> Good to have you here. I'm sure I don't
know if it's cold there in Michigan, but
it is absolutely We are in the south and
it is
>> weird weather. weird weather.
>> Cold and I'm like
>> all kinds of
>> it's it's bipolar. Yeah. Okay. The
weather's like up and down.
>> Uh Anguila. Barbara from Anguila. Always
good to see you here. Barbara, we have
Pas uh Pasco Washington.
>> That's Ross. Brother Ross.
>> Oh yeah, Brother Ross. Sorry. Sorry. Of
course. Our dear members. Sorry, Ross. I
just saw the name. I didn't look up at
the the name of the area, not the person
who was sending it. I apologize. Um,
that's Serbia. Yeah, from Serbia.
Wow, quite the international church.
Welcome.
>> We are so happy to have all of you here.
>> So good to see you guys. Um,
>> yes,
>> it was great to have a week off last
week, but we were fully blessed. And I
from what I've heard the from the
responses, you guys were blessed, too.
So, if you guys missed it, those of you
who didn't uh tune in for some reason,
go back and watch last week's service
because the youth did the entire
service, the sermon, the Sabbath school,
the announcements, the prayer. They were
amazing. So, we praise God for that.
>> So, uh you know, as um Sister Melinda
was here, uh and uh doing her sermon and
I remember as I was listening to her
>> Yeah. Um
>> she was in studio when she
>> Yeah.
>> I uh I thought to myself like this was
her first full sermon and we had told
her, "Yeah, you know, about 40 minutes
or so."
>> Yeah. She told me I said, "Hey, Melinda,
how long do you think your sermon is?"
She was like like 40 minutes. Yeah. I
was like, "Okay." Mhm.
And uh after she finished her sermon, I
told her that uh my very first sermon,
the very first sermon I ever preached
was two hours long. Two hours long. And
I think I put everything I knew about
Adventism up to that point
>> in that one sermon. Everything I knew in
the Bible was in that one sermon.
>> And this is uh before I became a pastor,
right? So,
>> I remember thinking to myself like it
took me about two to three weeks to put
the sermon together.
>> First sermon ever. And I just thought,
man,
>> I'm supposed to do this every seven days
for years and years and years. And I
just was like, how in the how in the
world am I going to be able to put
together a sermon, you know,
>> every seven days that's going to be uh
meaningful?
uh you know move people. And so when I
saw when when she preached for the first
time like her first full sermon and
>> it was an hour and 50 52 minutes
>> I was like all right I see you.
>> But that sermon moved like it didn't
feel like an hour and 52 minutes.
>> Nope.
>> It didn't.
>> And and all of the stories and she
>> and she didn't realize she could
>> she didn't she was like what
>> for an hour and 52 minutes.
>> But it was it was great. But it was a
beautiful sermon.
>> It was a beautiful sermon. And um she's
a natural guys.
>> A very natural.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and yeah. So we just keep her in
prayer. Keep her in prayer. All of them
because they all are just amazing young
people and have yet God is using all of
them. They're all very talented.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> I was impressed with Michaela. You you
did a great job on announcements.
>> Yep.
>> It's not easy.
>> Oh, I'm just talking because the way
that they
>> Oh, yeah. The energy. Oh yes, it was
beautiful.
>> And you know, I knew at the beginning
they were not they weren't having
technical difficulties, but they were
just trying to like um when you're live,
if you guys ever do a live thing like
we're doing right now, the whole thing
is you can't have dead air. Those are in
any type of broadcasting, if you've done
anything in that field, you know what
I'm talking about. So Michaela just like
kept it going and did a great job.
>> Yeah. I don't know if she's ever done
anything like that before
>> because you know I mean I went to school
for all of that and but she did a great
job to keep it going and I was a little
nervous. I was like what if something
happens and they don't know what to do
but God is good and they're very
talented. Amen. So praise God.
>> Amen. Amen.
>> Yes. I think when we as we were talking
there were some
>> praise God for the parents raising them.
>> Oh yes. Yes.
>> Oh yeah.
>> You guys are doing a great job.
>> Amen.
>> Doing a great job. Praise God. I know
Australia is here, too. So, we're down
under and we're we're just all over the
world.
>> Amen. Amen. Um, I just wanted to
mention, I mean, we don't have a date,
you guys, because of the Well, the
government's open now, so praise God for
that, but it wasn't at the beginning of
last week. So, the baptisms did get
postponed because people were coming
from all over and the flying situations
were wild. So, uh, but we are trying and
to see if we can get everyone scheduled.
>> I know it's kind of wild, but before
Christmas, um, in December. So, we we
are still we still are we have not had
our baptism. Um, the one that we were
supposed to have last week did not
happen and it will be happening soon.
So, just to give you guys an update on
that and t-shirt,
>> pray, wait, trust God has a plan.
>> Yes. So, man, there's two different ways
I could have went with this today, but
I'll go this way. Um, was listening to a
sermon this morning um by Pastor um I
think I say his name wrong, but Pavl
Goya.
>> So, um and it was just so powerful on
prayer and we're going to get him here.
We're we're inviting him to come here
because he needs to come.
>> He doesn't know that yet.
>> He doesn't. Yeah. If he's watching or if
somebody shares it with him, you're
you're gonna be invited here soon. Uh
but it was really powerful and um he was
just sharing
like we think faith is
he said something like we can have uh we
think faith is manipulating God's will.
I mean that's kind of how we think about
it sometimes or like oh if he answers my
prayer my way
>> I'll have I have faith in that you're
going to do that. Um, but he wants us to
have faith and trust him even when it is
to just trust his will whether it goes
the way that you were initially praying
or if it goes another way. That's true
faith.
>> True faith is to be like, man, you did
not answer it the way I was praying.
Now I have to choose to continue to have
faith
>> in your decision.
>> That's when faith is hard. Yeah,
>> that's when faith is hard. But that's
the kind of faith
>> you the way you put it after you heard
him was faith is uh trusting God even
when you don't understand what he's
doing.
>> Yes,
>> that is the way I said it to you this
morning.
>> So, yeah. And so, that's that's a
challenge. That's a challenge for for
all of us. But that's the type of faith
that we that we need when we pray
>> and trust. I love the words to a song
when you can't when you don't understand
what God is doing, trust his heart. So,
it goes back to getting a PhD in God's
character to be like, "All right, God, I
know you don't do anything that's not
going to be good for for me or the
situation because I trust your character
>> and so I have to trust you through the
way that you decided to answer this
prayer and trust that he knows best."
>> Yeah. So
>> that is just the challenge to encourage
us all to trust God through very
difficult situations when it doesn't go
the way that we we thought it should.
>> So
>> all right, we are going to
had a little bit of like a a change of
plans and we giving our panel the
Sabbath off. Uh we are going we're
actually doing question and answers. So,
if you guys signed up to get text
alerts, you got text alerts early this
morning saying, "Hey, if you have Bible
questions or mental health questions,
this is what we're doing for Sabbath
School." And we've got in a few. But I
also want to let you know that you can
put it in the chat if you want, but you
can also you can also send in your
question and we'll get them
live, but you can text uh to 855.
Remember this guys, write it down if you
think you have a question, but
855207-4107.
There you go. It's on the screen. Thank
you guys. Um, just text question and
then that will set you up to be able to
send in your question and that will be
sent to us and we can answer live. And
if we don't answer live today, we will
answer um on another question and answer
Sabbath, which we're planning to still
do once a month because the book, The
Christian Art of War, such a blessing.
We're continuing to go through that. Uh,
but we're going to take your questions
once a month and as we are continuing to
go through the book because we're moving
at a Holy Spirit pace. So, it may take
us a while. We're just in chapter four,
but it's such a blessing. We don't want
to rush it. Uh, but we also want to take
your questions. So, there's the text. I
think that's the number to text. That's
great. If you don't want to put it in
the chat and you just want to do that,
you can send us the question. I'm taking
mental health, relationship questions.
He's taking all things Bible.
>> That's right.
>> Yes. So, we're That's what we're doing
for Sabbath school today. All right, we
can pray.
>> All right.
Uh let's pray. Heavenly Father, thank
you, Lord, for giving us another
opportunity to uh worship you, Lord. We
pray that uh as we uh get into the word
this morning uh answering questions,
Lord, and um uh just dealing with uh uh
things from the Bible and things with
relationships and even mental health.
Lord, I pray that you would guide our
answers, guide our thoughts, Lord, guide
our discussion. And again, Lord, we
thank you for your love for us. In Jesus
name we pray. Amen.
>> Amen.
>> All right. So, you gonna go first?
>> I will go first.
>> All right.
>> Okay. So, uh this first question
actually is um
when I saw it this morning and as I
began to like think it through,
>> um I thought this might very well be my
uh evangelism Sabbath
sermon.
>> All right.
>> Uh for next week. Okay.
>> Last uh Sabbath of the month and uh
yeah.
>> Okay. So
>> my dates are
>> the question is a very simple question
but as I was thinking through and a
certain analogy came to my mind and I
was just like wow that's I think I might
preach on that. So you know you didn't
hear that. You're just yeah
you'll just be surprised next week.
Here's a question. In Matthew 24:14
points to this gospel or this good news
to be preached to all nations and then
the end will come. What is this gospel?
Do you think as Christians we are
complicating the gospel?
>> So it seems like a like a simple
question.
>> Um but I think uh
and and the question itself is asking do
we make it more complicated
than it needs to be. So in both ways,
you know, I think we're kind of like,
listen, if the gospel,
shouldn't the gospel gospel be simple?
And if it's simple, why do we complicate
it?
>> Uh so that's a very
>> good question.
>> It's a good question.
And the answer is that it is both simple
and yet complex. Right? There's a reason
that we're going to be studying the
gospel throughout all ages of eternity,
right? If it was like something like
just simple,
>> um, one study might suffice,
>> but we're going to be studying the theme
of salvation throughout all of eternity,
and it will continue to unfold uh,
powerful truths um, for God's people
throughout eternity.
>> Okay. So,
um, to really answer this question, I'm
going to do the nutshell first, right?
Uh, the atom, if you will, of the
gospel, like the smallest unit of
matter, uh, is is the atom. If we were
to break it down,
>> right, to its simplest form, uh,
Colossians or 1 Corinthians 1:23 says
this, "But we preach Christ crucified
unto the Jews, a stumbling block, and
unto the Greeks, foolishness."
Um, 1 Corinthians 2:2, for I determined
not to know anything among you, save
Jesus Christ and him crucified. The
everlasting gospel, the gospel in its
simplest form
uh is Christ crucified,
>> right? It's the cross.
So
that is if you want the simplest answer,
breaking it down to its uh most
irreducible level,
the cross. what Jesus did for us at the
cross is the gospel. All right. So, if
that makes sense, uh, put a one in the
chat and then I'm gonna move to my
second answer to that question.
>> Okay. So, here's a one.
>> So, I got a one over there. Um, and
we're looking in the chat to see, hey,
that's pretty pretty simple, pastor. We
get it. what Christ did at the cross is
the basic level of
um of understanding of what the gospel
is.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay. All right. So, I see the ones
coming. Now,
even though the atom is the smallest
unit of matter,
>> right?
There's actually stuff in the atom
>> that makes up the atom.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> So, you got your protons and your
neutrons and your electrons and now all
of those are the behind the scenes of
the atom. Mhm.
>> So while the cross
is the basic lowest irreducible
level of the plan of salvation
>> within the cross is a whole science
>> I like that
>> of salvation. Okay. So, as the atom
is the smallest level of matter, the the
the tiniest level of of matter, like if
you break it down, it's no longer an
atom, right?
>> It no longer is is considered matter.
Um, within that atom, that atom is made
up of certain things that if they're not
there, it's not an atom,
>> right? It's indivisible. You can't
divide these things. You separate one
thing, it's no longer an atom,
>> right?
So
what is what is the the workings of the
gospel? Where is that? Where can we find
the workings or how the cross itself
works? And the answer to that is
>> Go ahead.
>> I was going to say that Adam is love. I
mean that's like the
>> Do you know what I mean? Like
>> the Adam is love. The Adam is Christ.
You know, for God so loved the world
>> that he gave his only begotten son that
whosoever believeth in him should not
perish but have everlasting life. That
is personified in the cross.
>> Right?
>> Okay. So the cross is the Adam,
>> but within the cross
there's an entire system at work.
>> Like what does love look like
>> when you're
>> and do you see what I'm saying? Like,
>> so
>> what does it look like when you're
interacting with when you deal with
people or on how you
>> So,
>> I know I'm going into a whole thing, but
I'm just saying like Okay. Okay. Go
ahead.
>> So, what what I'm saying is that
>> other way
>> almost re
>> without even bringing us into the
picture yet,
>> right?
>> What does the gospel accomplish for the
believer?
and
>> changes your heart.
>> It changes your heart
>> and makes you love.
>> Yes.
>> And love God. Love God.
>> Yeah.
>> It makes you want to respond to God. But
go ahead.
>> The sanctuary.
>> Your question.
>> The sanctuary is the inner workings of
the cross. Mhm.
>> So that when you actually look at the
sanctuary service, and for th those of
you that have seen my blueprint
presentation before, seen me present on
the sanctuary, um you'll know that I I'm
really big on
the articles of furniture and how they
form the shape of the cross.
>> Yes.
>> Right. So then what that's telling us is
that the way the cross works,
>> the inner workings of the cross is found
in the sanctuary. The sanctuary is your
proton and electron and neutron, right?
That's what is going to reveal to us
what the gospel actually does. So the
atom itself is the cross.
>> But the sanctuary reveals how the cross
works,
>> right?
>> Yes.
>> So you have the altar of sacrifice which
is showing us behind the cross,
>> right? Mhm.
>> Behind the science of the cross
>> was Jesus's self-sacrificing love.
>> Yes.
>> Right. Behind the the behind the science
of the behind the atom of the cross is
Jesus washing us from our sins.
>> Behind the the the atom of the cross is
Jesus nourishing and bringing us the
bread of life so that we may live.
Behind the Adam of the cross is the the
Jesus's prayer uh his intercession on
our behalf. Behind the Adam of the cross
is Jesus taking us out of darkness and
moving us into light. And behind the the
the the the Adam of the cross is God's
desire to write the law on our hearts
and in our minds. So then
the gospel itself,
the frontfacing part of the gospel, the
visible part of the gospel is Christ and
him crucified. Right?
But what does that mean?
How does the atom work?
When we go into the sanctuary,
we see the inner workings of the gospel.
>> So here's what this means again,
everyone.
If you try to take away any part of the
inner workings of the of the of the
sanctuary, any part of the inner
workings of the atom, it's no longer an
atom. In the same way, remove the
candlestick from the gospel, and it's no
longer the gospel.
Remove the the altar of incense
uh from the picture of salvation, the
gospel, and it's no longer the gospel.
remove the ark of the covenant with the
law of God and it's no longer the
gospel.
>> The sanctuary
becomes the indivisible
unit that makes up what the gospel is.
>> Right? So here's what's happening you
guys. A lot of people are taking a
gospel into the world which only focuses
on one article of furniture. That is the
altar of sacrifice. So, hey, as long as
you believe that Jesus died for your
sins, you're good to go.
You're good to go,
>> right? Um, hey, don't worry about
the labor. Christ cleansing you,
actually cleansing you from your sins,
>> Christ pulling you out of a lifestyle
that is that is sinful, that is
defiling. Don't worry about that. Just
as long as you accept Christ. Or, hey,
don't worry about the law of God. uh the
ten commandments were done away with.
But anytime you take away any one of
those elements, you're taking away the
gospel,
>> right?
>> Remove one element, it's no longer an
Adam. Remove one element, it is no
longer the gospel.
>> So in its simplest form, then the gospel
is the cross.
>> Yes.
But to understand the actual inner
workings of the cross, you have to
understand every article of furniture in
the sanctuary which forms the shape of
the cross. It's literally the sanctuary
is literally saying see the cross,
right? That the the the uh altar of
sacrifice and then the labor and then
the altar of incense and the table of
showbread and the candlestick and the uh
ark of the covenant and the most holy
place. It forms the shape of the cross,
>> right? So all of remove one, you've
broken the cross.
>> Yes.
>> Remove one, you've divided the cross,
and now it's no longer the gospel.
>> And you need the whole cross.
>> You need the whole cross. Meaning you
need every aspect of the sanctuary to
tell us this is what the gospel actually
is. So when people try to separate the
law of God and say, "Oh, that's not the
gospel."
>> They're wrong.
And people try to separate uh uh um you
know anything other than as long as you
accept Christ, you don't need these
other articles of furniture, you've just
destroyed the atom.
>> Right.
>> And when you split the atom,
>> if I understand it correctly, you cause
destruction.
>> Yes.
>> Right.
>> Oh yes.
A lot of people are walking around with
a destructive form of the gospel
>> that is not saving but destroying.
>> All right. So,
>> good answer.
>> Question one.
>> Question one. Okay,
>> that makes sense. Everybody just uh
>> it made sense to me.
>> Put a one in the chat
>> and uh
>> it made sense to me.
>> Okay. Um I have a question here. Barrett
says, "I have just experienced one of
the most stressful weeks on my job. Um,
what are some practical ways to deal
with stress in the moment?" So, um, you
know, when we're stressed, our cortisol
levels are way up here high. So, one way
to bring that down low, like right away,
like immediately, is to do, and you guys
have heard me talk about this, but
breathing techniques. So I like to teach
people to do 479. So that's taking a
deep breath for four counts. Taking a
deep breath and then hold your breath
for seven counts and then release it for
nine counts. Like you're letting all the
oxygen out of your lungs like a balloon
deflating. Do that three times. You can
do that at your desk, you know, because
you're at work, right? So you're
stressed. So you can't, you know, so
you're just trying to do something
really quick. That's going to
automatically lower your heart rate,
slow your heart rate down and bring that
those levels, the cortisol, the stress
levels down like immediately once you do
that. And if you need to do it more than
three times, then you do it more until
you're just feeling calm and relaxed.
And when you do that, it because when
you're stressed, like how you're saying
it's a very stressful week at work and
at or in any situation, it's this part
of your brain, the preffrontal cortex
part of your brain is
um you're not really operating out of
that part of your brain. You're
stressed, you're having anxiety, like
so, you know, it's like the fire alarm
in your brain is going off like
everything's a problem. Um, but when you
brea do that breathing technique, um, it
actually
shuts the fire alarm off, calms you
down, and opens up the prefrontal cortex
part of your brain. So, you can be like,
"Okay, I'm at work. My boss just asked
me to do a a very difficult task or my
co-worker is being annoying or whatever
the stress is causing you, but let me
respond
in a good way and just do one thing at a
time or whatever the case is to just,
you know, be calm. It has you
approaching the situation in a mature uh
in a mature way. Um the other thing that
you can do in a stressful time,
especially because I'm gonna I'm going
on work because you said work. So, you
can go into the bathroom and splash cold
water on your face. What is that going
to do? That is going to cause a dopamine
release in your brain. Why does it cause
a dopamine release in your brain?
Because um it's based dopamine is based
off of a pain pleasure principle. So,
when you do the cold water on your face,
the brain is like, "Oh no, if you did
it, Ivor's Ivor is hurting. He's in
pain. Let me send dopamine." And so it
it just helps you. So you get the
dopamine, you feel better. When you feel
better, you can approach a situation
better. You're going to respond better,
act better, deal with stress in a
healthy way. So that's a quick little
thing that you can do. You can do when
you're at work in any situation. Yeah.
>> You can do the breathing absolutely
anywhere. You don't always have the cold
water, but there's bathrooms everywhere
almost. So,
>> and then we we actually did an entire
series on the sanctuary and um
>> with like three and a half. Yeah. With
Dr. White
>> and dealing with stress.
>> Thought it was marriage. We did stress.
>> I think we did stress because we were
talking about we can do it with stress.
>> Yeah. How each one of the articles, you
know, like
>> Yes. I'm remembering
>> laying the uh laying your stressors on
the altar of sacrifice.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Yeah. Right.
>> Definitely. And and a lot of us, you
know, you were listening to this this
morning as well about Abraham
>> um laying Isaac on the altar and how
man, I don't want to do that. And for a
lot of us,
>> we we we love our sin and our stressors
>> like Abraham loves Isaac. Like, do I
have to?
>> And yeah,
>> you know, being willing to put that on
the altar
>> um
>> takes
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> real commitment to God.
>> And so just learning, all right, Lord,
here's this thing.
>> Every day I take it up and I, you know,
I hate it and yet I love it at the same
time. I carry it.
>> We don't leave it at the feet of Jesus.
We take it to him. We take it to Jesus,
pray about it, and then we pick it right
back up.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And, you know, it's so
funny. We talk about We talk about, you
know, take bring your sins to the foot
of the cross,
>> right? And again,
>> we be carrying, we'd be leaving the
cross carrying stuff all, you know,
>> but the foot of the cross literally
parallels with the altar of sacrifice.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. If you stand the sanctuary up and
look at it from a bird's eye view,
>> the the head of the cross is the is the
ark of the is the ark of the covenant.
The foot of the cross
>> is the altar of sacrifice.
>> Yes.
>> So, think of it when we're told, "Hey,
bring that to the foot of the cross."
Mhm.
>> You're actually bringing it to the altar
of sacrifice to lay it on the altar and
sacrifice it. Walk away from it.
>> Um and there's no better thing to do
with stress than to lay it on the altar.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Um and
I just got a text that says I guess the
question was pertaining more to anger,
not stress, but my answer is the same.
>> Same. So there it is. No, it's the same.
Um, it's stress and anger. I mean, the
body or the brain doesn't be like, "Oh,
you're stressed." Or, "Oh, you're
angry." It's it's it's computing every
It's all the same in your mind or how it
affects, let me not say it that way, how
it impacts your brain or mind. It's all
the same. Um, it doesn't the brain
doesn't know to how to differentiate
between anger and stress. Um I like to
use the example like even when we
um yeah even when we are grieving like
the body doesn't know like oh you're
grieving because you lost a loved one or
if you're depressed. It doesn't know the
difference between grief and depression.
>> It's just it is phys it does have a
physical impact on your body.
>> Yeah.
>> So all right but thank you for
correcting that.
>> Okay. And there's so many questions
coming up in in the chat
>> but I'm missing them all. But let's but
let me I Okay,
>> we're gonna We
>> They're mental health ones. I don't want
to miss them. Are they mental health or
for you?
>> Uh I I've just been seeing a whole bunch
of question marks just question mark. I
saw no questions coming. I don't know
who they're, you know, directed to, but
>> you go to your next one and I'll I'll
check that.
>> We we are going to be pulling these
questions
uh from the chat so that the next time
we do a question and answer uh we'll
have these questions that uh that we
will get to. Okay.
>> Yes. And then you can if you Yeah. If
you do have a mental health or Bible
question, there's the number there on
the screen. And I also want to say to
John Hazley
that you're right that deep breath is a
he was said that he was taught to do a
belly breath. But you're taking a deep
breath. So you're taking it from the
lower part of your abdomen for sure.
That's the that's where you take the
deep breath. But go ahead.
>> Okay. Um All right. So here's a question
um regarding the Sabbath. So it says if
I do if I don't observe the Sabbath, can
that jeopardize my eternal life? If I
don't if it doesn't jeopardize my
eternal life, why am I obligated to
observe the Sabbath every Saturday
starting on Friday? So that's another
pretty uh potent and loaded question,
right? Because
>> I think it comes, you know, what this
question brings into play. Um how are we
saved?
Um, and it kind of goes right back to
that question of the gospel. You know,
what is the gospel? So, I'm going to
expound on what I just explained in
terms of what the gospel is, right? We
just saw that
um the gospel
includes
the sacrifice of Christ at the at the
altar of sacrifice.
It includes
cleansing from sin which which we see is
what the labor teaches. Uh and it
includes
the the uh Christ's intercession on our
on our behalf. That's what happens at
the altar of incense. It includes being
transformed by the word of God. That's a
table of showbread. And it includes
>> drawing us out of darkness into his
marvelous light. That's the altar of
incense. You cannot have the gospel and
remove any one of those things. Right.
>> Yeah.
>> The ark of the covenant is where the law
of God is contained in the sanctuary.
>> To remove the ark of the covenant,
you're removing not just the ark, but
you're also removing the mercy seat. And
and that's a very important point for us
to understand, right?
The law of God which was found in the
ark and the mercy seat go together
>> and there's a reason why especially in
the context of sin. So to this question
if I don't observe the Sabbath can that
jeopardize my eternal life?
>> Put remove the I would say remove the
Sabbath commandment and just put any one
of the other commandments in there.
put stealing or lying
um or coveting,
>> right? Um
if
can lying
cause you to be lost? Can killing cause
you to be lost? Can adultery cause you
to be lost? And the obvious answer is
yes. They can definitely cause you to be
lost. In fact, in Revelation 22:14,
the Bible says, "Blessed are they that
do his commandments that they may have
right
to the tree of life and may enter in
through the gates into the city."
>> So the question is, what is it that
gives the people right to enter into the
city? Is it the keeping of the
commandments? And I'm going to say, no,
it's actually not the keeping of the
commandments. M
>> the keeping of the commandments do not
grant us right
a right to enter into the city because
if keeping the commandments was the
basis for us entering into the city then
everybody would be lost
because
all have sinned and fallen short of the
glory of God. I was explaining to
someone um just uh uh a couple days ago.
We were talking about this idea of
salvation and this theme of salvation
and I was sharing that listen a murderer
cannot make things right by never
killing again.
>> Right? Hey, I'm going to if a murderer
says for the rest of my life I'm never
going to kill again. You've already
taken a life. No matter how much you do
in the future, none of that can atone
>> for the fact that you've already broken
the law. And that's how it is with God.
Once we have sinned, we are under the
wages of death,
>> right?
>> Yes.
>> Nothing you can do. If you if you were
perfect from today
to the end of your life, you still could
not stand before God and say, "Look,
God, look at the record of my perfection
from this age till the end of my life.
Why? Because God
demands absolute perfection.
The law demands absolute perfection.
>> Once you've sinned once, absolute
perfection is no longer possible. Right?
>> Because you have already the the clay
has already been marred.
So
why does the Bible then say that those
who keep the commandments will have a
right to the tree of life? Here's the
reason why. In Exodus chapter 20, right
in the middle of the third commandment,
the Bible says this word, this the Bible
reads this, "Showing mercy
unto thousands of them that love me and
keep my commandments." Okay, so let's
let's understand this.
Everyone who keeps God's commandments
are already guilty of sin because all
have sinned and fallen short of the
glory of God.
So when they are saved and they realize
salvation includes having the law of God
written on my heart. It includes
accepting Christ's sacrifice at the
labor. It includes being transformed by
the word. It includes having my sins
washed away at the labor. It includes
Christ's intercession at the altar of
incense. It includes me coming out of
darkness into his marvelous light at the
at the altar at the seven branch
candlestick.
Once you understand that
this entire thing is what makes up the
gospel, but you've already sinned, you
now realize that any chance of you being
saved is strictly by the mercy of God.
That's it.
No one no one wants to stand before God
>> and say, "God, give me justice." What
they're going to say is, "God, give me
mercy."
>> Because all have sinned and fallen short
of the glory of God. None of us are
going to be able to say, "Look, I kept
the Sabbath. Uh uh uh every day since I
understood I kept the Sabbath. Every
seventh day since I understood the
Sabbath truth, I I stopped killing. I
stopped." None of us are going to be
able to say because I stopped breaking
your law, I should be worthy of entering
into heaven.
>> So, what I'm saying is remove the
Sabbath question. Don't focus on the
Sabbath. Focus on the entire law of God.
>> Right?
>> Does this mean that we no longer need to
keep the law of God? Absolutely not.
>> Those who are forgiven
show that the mercy of God is working in
them. show that that that the love of
God is working in them in that they're
now like I'm changing my life.
>> Even though I know that changing my life
is not what is going to earn me heaven,
it was the death, burial, and
resurrection of Christ. My thank you
>> to Jesus. My my my
devotion to what he's done for me is I'm
going to live like him.
>> He kept the Sabbath. I'm keeping the
Sabbath. He didn't lie. I'm not going to
lie. He didn't steal. I'mma stop
stealing. He didn't kill. He didn't get
angry. I'm going to stop getting angry.
And if I happen to fall in one of those
things, I know that if I ask for
forgiveness and repent and turn away
from breaking that law, that God is
going to forgive me.
>> But here's the key thing.
The text in Ezekiel 20 says in in Exodus
20 says, "Showing mercy unto thousands
of them that love me and keep my
commandments." Mhm.
>> So, who gets mercy?
Those that keep his commandments.
When the Bible says, "Blessed are they
that do his commandments," the blessing
is not that they do his commandments.
The blessing is that they get mercy.
Does that make sense everybody? Mhm.
>> The blessing, the reason they are
blessed
in keeping the commandments is that God
extends mercy to those that keep his
commandments.
Those who say, "Hey, I don't need to
keep God's commandments."
>> Right?
>> Right. Because I'm already saved. I
don't need to keep. Don't understand the
fullness of the gospel.
>> Right?
They see the atom, the cross, but they
don't understand the inner workings. And
God is trying to get people. There's
some people who just don't understand it
because that's what they've been taught.
They've been taught, hey, there's no
inner workings in the cross. It's just
the cross. Jesus died for you and that's
it. You're good to go.
>> Right? So that's one of the reasons why
we try to teach and instruct and God
sends out you know the everlasting
gospel to correct to under to to to
bring a correct understanding of what
the gospel actually does in the life.
Mhm.
>> So in a nutshell then and I know that
was a really really intense question.
>> Um
in a nutshell
what the gospel does
the the
we are saved by the mercy of God. Mhm.
>> But that mercy is extended to those
who are operating within the operating
system of the cross.
>> I've accepted Christ's sacrifice.
>> Right? I believe that his his death has
washed me from my sins.
>> Uh I've received his word.
I I I I I
plead for him
to be my intercessor.
>> I want him to draw me out of darkness
into his light.
>> Amen.
>> And I and I accept him wanting to write
his law on my heart and in my mind.
Again,
the keeping of the commandments don't
save you, but the breaking of them will
get you lost.
>> Right?
>> What saves you is mercy.
That mercy translates into Lord, I'm
going to obey your will. Mhm.
>> And when we're obeying his will, it is
our demonstration that the gospel is
actually working within us.
So that question for the Sabbath should
be asked for all of God's commandments,
right? And here's what we learn. We're
not saved by keeping the commandments,
>> but those who break them are lost.
>> Right?
>> Those who say, "Hey, I I'm going to
kill. I'm going to lie. I want to live
my life in these ways. I want to ignore
this portion of the law of God or that
portion of the law of God. That is where
the Bible says that those who uh are
outside the city
>> are those who love a lie.
>> Right?
>> And Jesus said and John uh in first John
says uh he who says he loves me and
keeps not my commandments is a liar and
the truth is not in him. So, all of
these things go together. And there's
actually a part two to this question,
which I'm going to pause on for a
second.
>> I'm gonna go if you if you want me to
answer the part two, I can do that now.
But
>> maybe we should break it up.
>> All right.
>> I mean, if that's is the part too long.
You are the twohour pre sermon preacher.
So it's probably
>> the part two is the part two to this
question
>> is
why do adventists choose different laws
of the Old Testament when Jesus said in
the New Testament um you know love is a
fulfilling of the law.
>> Yes, we'll do part two.
>> We're going to come back to part two.
>> I'm gonna let her answer. Don't forget
everything I just said. Yeah,
>> I'm gonna come back to that.
>> Here we're still on the question. Don't
go anywhere.
Um,
a lot of different ways I can go here.
Okay, so let's Okay, so this is
a question. Um, can I see your glasses?
I did not break my glasses.
>> Go ahead.
>> So I can't completely see completely.
>> Okay, so the question is, is mental
illness demon possession? Um, like with
the demoniacs?
So an easy answer to that is absolutely
not. mental health illness or disorders
are not uh demon possession. Um
that's not even biblically.
>> Yeah, I think correct.
I think that is part of the taboo of
people not wanting to acknowledge that
they struggle with some some mental
health issue because
>> they're afraid it will be seen as you
know
>> like you're not close to God like if
you're depressed or anxious or
>> um if you struggle if you have you know
let's just say bipolar or um any other
uh disorder in the mental health
>> in the mental health field. So
>> there are physical attributes
I mean um of mental health like chemical
imbalances, things of that nature.
>> There's chemical imbalances. I mean we
we live in a world this is a sinful
world and so we're you know and so um
things aren't always clicking
um properly like in our minds and things
like that. Yeah,
>> you're being me now.
>> I know. But that's not to say that it
cannot manifest itself as mental
illness.
In other words, like you know there are
people who having done certain things or
live certain ways or you know demon
possession is real. That's what I'm
saying. Demon possession is real but you
have to be very careful of mental
illness,
>> right? You have to be very careful of,
you know, applying, you know, someone
who's str genuinely who's struggling
with mental illness and telling them
that that that they're demonpossessed,
>> right? And people thinking like, oh, we
could just pray, you know, prayer is
powerful and God is able to do anything.
Uh, but sometimes people heir on the
side of I'm not going to get mental
health help or get either let's just say
or my spouse or my child or a family
member mental health help because I just
believe I can just pray. Um, when I mean
God has just like you know with doctors,
God has empowered u mental health
professionals to be able to help and and
help in those type of situations. Um,
and there's nothing wrong of course we
can we can we should always pray. Um but
um it's just like if you need to go in
to an emergency room because your your
leg was just
cut off and you're bleeding to death,
you're not going to just pray. You're
going to be rushed to the hospital. So
>> um the bottom the the very simple answer
is no. It is not um the same thing. It
is not the same thing. Um, since you're
about to go for a long one, I could
>> And there's a question that just came up
about if a person is cutting, is that
demon possession?
>> It is. That's not Well, I think I should
answer that. That's not demon possession
either. Um,
>> so let me let me say this. In the Bible,
there are people that, you know, they
were demonp possessed and they were
doing that as a result of demon
possession.
>> That doesn't mean that everyone that
does that
>> is demonp possessed.
>> No.
>> Right. Um but there are other issues
there. So again
um and let me say this
understand that the devil is behind all
sickness, all illness. Right.
>> Right.
>> He's behind cancers. He's behind car
accidents. He's behind
>> cancer is his character turned into a
disease.
>> He's behind all ugly and nasty.
>> He's behind all disease. He's behind all
mental illness. All of those things. But
it doesn't it like a person with cancer
is not demonp possessed, right? No.
>> A person who is sick is not necessarily
demonp possessed. And that's true for
those who are sick mentally as well.
>> It's not a sign of demon possession.
>> No.
>> Even though demon possession can
manifest itself in in that way,
>> it is not a sign like okay well if
they're going through this then that
means there's demon possession. So going
back to the cutting uh scenario um so
when someone decides to cut
I would say now this I would say this
their faulty thinking which I believe
comes from the enemy which comes from
Satan is that like I feel so bad that I
can cause pain somewhere else and that
will help me feel a little bit better
and it will help almost transfer the
somewhere else and not just think about
the emotional because I'll be physically
hurting. It's a faulty way to think. It
is not healthy. It's not the way God
wants us to think. Um but um that is
that is what the enemy does in
situations like that. Um but that can
that's if somebody is cutting, they need
to be seeing a mental health
professional to deal with why they are
cutting. Um, and it's, you know, it's
it's coming from depression, anxiety,
um,
many times. Um, not
not, um, it's not necess necessarily a
an official attempt of suicide and not
wanting to be here. It's more of like I
just want the pain to stop. Um, but it
is a very dangerous thing. at me because
you can cut so far that you can cause
permanent injury and even death because
you can rupture a artery and all those
type of things. So
>> I think you can cut in the wrong place.
So I'm just saying that you don't take
that lightly. Um if if somebody is
cutting they definitely need to see a
mental health professional because it is
>> um you know it's not a healthy situation
but it is not um demonic possession.
But I do believe that uh at the same
time uh it is the it is the devil
telling lies.
>> Well, all every sin that we do
originates with him. And so in that in
that in that if we're going to go there
with it,
>> we're all
>> correct.
>> We're all a little possessed at times
like when we're yelling and arguing and
that's
>> the temptation. That's Satan.
>> Yeah. So, and a lot of times
>> it all comes from him.
>> Yeah. And a lot of times we we look at
demon possession
the way that Hollywood
paints demon possession, right? Um but
remember, Judas was demonp possessed and
was in con he was he wasn't foaming at
the mouth.
>> He wasn't,
>> you know what I'm saying? He wasn't like
his eyes weren't doing weird things. He
was just demonpossessed, but as calm as
ever,
>> right? Mhm.
>> Um, the Pharisees were demonpossessed.
>> So,
again, our idea of demon possession, I
think, is often limited to you're
foaming at the mouth. You know, you're
you're acting real crazy and really
supernatural crazy things are happening.
But, as you said,
>> when we're sinning, sometimes we looking
really crazy and acting crazy. I mean,
it's
>> Yeah. But you can be demonpossessed and
looked absolutely normal. And you know,
take Judas as the prime example of demon
possession.
>> Yeah.
>> Um so
>> um
I think that
a lot of times when we struggle with
depression, we're listening uh to, you
know, the devil's telling us lies about
ourselves, about our worth,
>> um all of those things, right?
So
anyway, I think you've you know that I
think they've gotten the point, right?
>> Yes. No,
>> we don't just want to be like, "Yeah,
you're demonpossessed." And
>> right,
>> you know, yeah, we we need to be
sensitive and
>> and look at the situation and, you know,
ask for God's wisdom um on how to help,
you know, our loved ones that are going
through something
>> uh of a mental nature like that.
>> Yeah. and uh you know allow the Lord to
lead.
>> I'm gonna let you answer your question.
>> My next question, part two of the
question is um so why do Adventists
choose certain laws uh from the Old
Testament
>> and uh when when Jesus says that love
um is the fulfilling of the law.
>> You know Jesus said the two great
commandments are love God and love your
neighbor. So um number one those two
commandments are actually taken from the
old testament
>> so that they are not new commandments.
Uh in the old testament um let's see I
think it's Deuteronomy 6:4 says here O
Israel the Lord our God is one and thou
shalt love the Lord thy God with all
thine heart and with all thy soul and
with all thy might. So this is not a new
commandment. Um
uh
this is not a new commandment in the
sense of they had never heard it before.
>> This Jesus is quoting from the Old
Testament. Okay. Uh love your neighbor
as yourself. That's Leviticus 19:18.
19:18 which tells us that we're to love
our neighbor as ourselves.
This is not a new commandment. This is
Jesus quoting from the Old Testament.
>> Right? And remember that when Jesus is
alive, they don't have a New Testament.
>> So if people are going to test Jesus by
the word, you know,
>> what word are they testing him by? What
they have in the Old Testament, right?
So remember this then the early church,
the scriptures of the early church
was the Old Testament.
If you cannot find the gospel in the Old
Testament, if you cannot find the
teachings of Jesus in the Old Testament,
if your understanding of the teachings
of Jesus originate in the New Testament,
>> then there's a very serious problem,
>> right?
>> Because the early church, the book of
Acts, I mean the the the in the book of
Acts, when the spirit is poured out upon
them, there is no New Testament book of
of there is no New Testament of the
Bible. It's strictly the Old Testament.
Mhm.
>> That means then that if the gospel was
was set during the book of uh in the
book of Acts,
all of their teachings, all of their
understanding of grace and mercy, all of
those things would have to be found in
the Old Testament. So that's number one.
>> Number two, or actually that's number
two. Number one is that Jesus is quoting
from the Old Testament when he when he
when he gives those two laws. Number two
is that all of the teachings of Christ
were based on the old old uh testament.
>> And when we understand that, this third
point really is what how we determine
what laws still stand and what laws
don't. So, I'm going to try to break
this down in as simple a way as I can.
Okay?
In the Old Testament when the when God
sets aside the children of Israel, there
are certain things
uh there are laws that he gives them
many laws.
>> Uh 623 laws, something to that nature uh
in all, but those laws
all have different functions.
And I'm not going to get into all of
those laws. I'm simply going to say this
that many of those laws
could not be kept outside of Israel,
>> right? Outside of Israel as a nation,
those laws were specifically geared
toward Israelites living in Israel.
>> So, for example, Passover could not be
kept anywhere. Sacrifices could not
happen anywhere. You couldn't just be
like, "Hey, you know, I'm going to uh
I'm going to go to uh to Mido Persia,
and I think while I'm there, I'm going
to, you know, celebrate uh the the I'm
going to uh celebrate Passover or No,
the feasts
had to be kept. They sacrifices were
connected with the feasts and these
feasts had to be held
>> at the sanctuary in Jerusalem. Right? So
when you understand that if there was no
temple and if there was no Israel, all
of those laws are immediately done away
with.
>> Right? In 70 AD when the temple is
destroyed and Jerusalem is destroyed,
all the laws that were connected with
the temple and with Jerusalem
>> done away. Right? When Jesus died on the
cross,
all the laws connected with the temple
because the veil rent in the temple.
>> Jesus was was God was showing look the
temple is of no more significance.
>> Every law connected with the temple,
sacrifices, feast days, um uh um feasts
of tabernacles, all of these feasts were
done away with. But the Israelites
didn't believe that. So they just kept
doing it anyway. And so in 70 AD when
Rome destroys Jerusalem and the temple
now there literally is no way that they
can observe these laws.
>> Now having said that the ten
commandments
stand on a totally different level than
all those laws.
>> There was no temple. There is no
requirement to have a temple standing in
order to keep the ten commandments. The
Sabbath commandment out of all the other
feast days, the Sabbath commandment was
the only one given when it was given. It
was not connected with the sacrifice.
>> You didn't have to have a sacrifice in
order to keep the Sabbath,
>> right?
>> And it was a universal commandment. You
could keep it anywhere.
>> You didn't have to be in Jerusalem to
keep it. Mhm.
>> Therefore, we know that when the when
Rome destroys Jerusalem, when the temple
is destroyed, every law connected with
the temple, Passover, unleven bread,
first fruits, Pentecost, feast of
trumpets, uh day of atonement, feast of
tabernacles can't be kept anymore. Why?
Because they all involve sacrifices and
the temple is destroyed. How can we
sacrifice? We can't just sacrifice
anywhere. It had to be in Jerusalem and
it had to be at the temple. Now you
understand
>> all those laws connected with the temple
in Jerusalem
>> done away with. But the ten commandments
which were universal in nature, which
were not dependent upon Jerusalem, which
were not dependent upon a sanctuary, you
could be anywhere in the world and not
kill, not steal, not lie, keep the
Sabbath. None of those commandments were
bound in a literal and local in a local
sense to Jerusalem in the temple. So
those are the laws that still stand. And
when Jesus is quoting to love God and to
love your neighbor, he's quoting, he's
summarizing the two tables of stone.
>> The first four, this is what you do if
you love God,
>> right?
>> You don't take his name in vain. You
don't have any other gods before him.
You don't make images to him. And you
remember the Sabbath to keep it holy.
>> The last six, that's what you do when
you love your neighbor. You won't lie,
you won't kill. You won't steal. you
honor your mother and father, you won't
cover it, etc.
>> So, this is not a new law. He's simply
saying the ten commandments still stand.
>> Yeah.
>> And I want to write them on your heart
so that you love God with all you have
and you love your neighbor as you love
yourself.
>> Amen.
>> And that is a conclusion of that
>> that two-part question.
>> Long two-part question.
>> Okay. All right.
>> Okay.
>> All right. I have a question. um
says marriage is in tr their marriage is
in trouble. Um how can I forgive my
spouse for having emotional affair? I
feel betrayed and have lost all trust.
So this is very challenging um indeed
especially when trust is broken whether
it is a um physical affair or emotional
affair it really doesn't matter. it's
trust is broken. Um, and it takes time
to build that trust back up. But there
are some criterias of for for
your spouse um moving forward like have
they
um are they very sorry for what they
have done in the sense that um they are
being completely transparent not you
know just very open and even willing to
go to therapy because I would say I
would tell anybody this and I'll just
take the risk to just do a broad sweep
deep and to say, listen, if you've had
an emo, if you're dealing with
infidelity and dealing with trust issues
because of an emotional affair or
physical affair, you need to be in in
therapy with your spouse. You need to
find um a very good licensed therapist.
Um because you're not going to be able
to fix this all on your own. There's so
many emotions and and different um
levels to
trying to get back to where you need to
be or not even getting back. Let's just
say you're starting something new
because obviously what you had maybe not
every single thing, but there was some
issues there. Somebody doesn't have an
emotional affair or physical affair.
They don't just wake up one morning and
be like, "Oh, everything's perfect. I
think I'm just going to go have an
affair." That typically does not happen.
So, there's other things going on. and
not blaming the spouse that was cheated
upon that like you're at fault, but
there were already issues in the
marriage. So, you need to go and get
professional help. If you're at home
just trying to deal with it on your own,
it's going to be extremely difficult and
you're just going to keep probably
reinjuring the situation because you're
not forgiving. I don't know if this is a
husband or a wife who did the had the
emotional affair, but the the spouse
that cheated you, you keep um the
situation keeps getting injured because
you're not trusting. So, every single
thing that they do, you don't believe
them. It's just like you can't open up
and allow yourself to fully feel safe
enough to have a loving, healthy
marriage again right now. But in therapy
and with God, that can happen again. But
it takes time.
It takes time. So, I'm sorry that that
happened to you and that you're in this
space, but um with God, all things are
possible. That's if the spouse that
committed the emotional affair is is is
in a healthy space where they're just
like, you know, I really messed up. I
want my I want our life back. I'm
willing to do whatever it takes and
allows God to work with them and within
your marriage together and with a mental
health professional working uh in
therapy on your marriage. It is very
difficult to do on your own. And if you
do it on your own, you might put a
little band-aid on it, but you never
really dealt with all the undercurrent
stuff. And so it's going to pop up later
on and you're going to have other issues
later.
>> And we
>> very possible that you could have other
issues later. It's very probable that
you'll have other issues later, but go
ahead.
>> So, we did do a whole series on marriage
>> marriage through the sanctuary
sanctuary. And you know that this
communication thread that I'm getting,
they corrected
that first one was on stress. It was
anger that we did through the sanctuary.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Anger and we did marriage. We did
both.
>> Yeah. So, just to add to what you just
said, um
remember that the sanctuary is
was God's way of fixing his marriage
with mankind,
>> right? And that's why
>> and they cheated.
>> Yeah. Sure.
>> The height of that day was called the
day of atonement or the day of at
onement which the purpose of it was to
bring atonement or at onement between
God and his separated people.
>> Right? So um if God fixes
his broken marriage, understand what I
mean when I say his broken marriage, not
that God was at all unfaithful, but man
was unfaithful. Mhm.
>> So God fixes his marriage through the
sanctuary, right? This how I'm going to
bring man back to me and how I'm going
to bring that union or bring about that
union between divinity and humanity.
Then I think those principles of the
sanctuary
are going to be extremely important
>> in the process of healing, you know,
your marriage.
>> Yes.
>> And and guess where it all starts? It
all starts at the altar of sacrifice
>> where if the if you know if the spouse
is not willing to lay that thing on the
altar and that repents confession right
>> about everything everything needs to be
on that altar. Everything.
>> Yeah.
>> That putting it on the altar and being
willing to lay it all on the altar.
If that step doesn't happen, everything
everything beyond that is uh
it's just not real, right? Everything is
going to depend upon how much you lay
upon that altar.
>> And if you're not laying the entire
thing on the altar, if you're keeping a
back a portion of it,
>> that's going to spring up
>> later on. Mhm.
>> So,
>> and really deal with the root cause to
why that was even an option. Mhm.
>> Um and and sometimes again it's not that
the other spouse
many times I mean it takes two the
marriage is two people and so um as I
say it takes two to tango I mean there's
different things going on but still it's
never an excuse to go and do um have an
affair emotional or physical and so
sometimes a lot of times the one that
committed the emotional affair the
spouse that did needs to be an
individual therapy and just see like
okay because what they did that wasn't
something that characteristic about them
that wasn't probably brand new in the
marriage. Not saying that they had
committed infidelity before and you know
that doesn't have to be the case but
there are other things in our past that
we bring into marriage whether it's
childhood traumas or different
experiences that definitely they were
never dealt with and that it could be
insecurities. It could be trust issues.
It could be so many things and so that
was never dealt with before the marriage
and so they brought it in the marriage
and it caused this. So they need to deal
with it that on an individual level and
then the couple together needs to work
on some things together. But
the marriage can be restored. It can be.
It's very possible. I mean I've seen
that happen
>> many times and
um I've seen people get divorced and get
married again. So I've seen even that
which is a lot of waste of money but you
know however it works out but just to
give hope to that. So even though you
feel really horribly now, um God can
heal even this horrible wound that
you're experiencing.
>> We have a good friend that uh
>> which friend are you talking about? I'm
not thinking
>> I can't say which friend I'm talking the
name, but I'm trying to think of I don't
know this friend.
>> And uh I just thought, you know, we
hadn't talked in a while about the
relationship, but I was like, "Yeah,
that relationship."
>> You thought it was over dead.
>> Yeah. It was like, "Yeah, this is done."
Like there's no way this is gonna be
fixed.
>> I kind of thought so, too. But then when
I asked it was like, "Oh yeaha." I'm
like, "Wow." Like God restored.
>> Like what?
>> Wow.
>> God restored. That's
>> So God is able to restore.
>> God restores. Amen. Amen. It's possible.
It's very possible.
>> I'm going to take one more question
because we're at we're at uh
>> we're at the time
>> 134. Yeah.
>> Really quick, I think I can do I'm This
isn't Oh, I'm sorry.
>> There's a whole bunch of questions. I'll
make this one will be short for me.
>> Okay. Go ahead. just want to be short.
Um, and you guys, I know there's
questions that I have in front of me
that that we haven't gotten to.
Questions that we're getting in text and
questions that we're seeing. We're going
to collect all these question.
>> Yeah, we're going to collect all of
them.
>> This is me too in a total on the spot
thing.
>> And I think we might do this next week
only because it's Thanksgiving weekend
and probably a lot of our panel will be
like family and blah blah blah. So,
>> there's a part two next week.
>> All right. So be it. All right. Um, so,
uh, I've heard some Christians teach
that Exodus 34:7 means that there are
generational curses.
Uh, and what it says is keeping keeping
steadfast love for thousands, forgiving
iniquity and transgression and sin, but
who will by no means clear the guilty,
visiting the iniquity of the fathers on
the children and the children's children
to the third and fourth generation. Um
so the question is do the sins of the
parents you know pass down to
uh the third and fourth generation
>> so generational curses.
>> Um I'm going to say that I don't believe
that that's what the text is teaching.
Um, what I believe the text is actually
saying is that um the
the
um
sins that parents
that the generation commits can have
effect and impact
on
your children and their children and
their children. Right? So knowing that
your children will I mean things that
you do can affect your children. Not
that they're going to pay for your sins,
>> but things that you do can affect your
children,
>> right? Absolutely. In other words, your
sins don't happen in a vacuum,
>> right? they affect
>> people around you.
>> So,
uh you know when the children of Israel
are in the wilderness and they they sin
that sin that their their children are
forced to be in the wilderness for an
extra 40 years.
>> Yeah.
>> Not because of their sins but because of
the sins of their parents. Right. So
it's not that they themselves had sinned
but they had to deal with the
consequences. And a lot of times we have
to deal with the consequences of uh you
know the consequences of our actions.
>> We could set bad examples for our
children
>> right that end up going
you know end up they take on those on
those attributes.
Not that it's passed down to them by
blood,
but your example can be detrimental to
your offspring and their offspring.
>> So, I think that's what the text is. Uh
the text is saying
>> and read the text again. I didn't
actually hear you read it because I was
looking at this stuff and so because I
do have a a followup, but I want you to
read it again.
>> Yeah. uh keeping steadfast love for
thousands, forgiving iniquity and
transgression and sin, but who will by
no means clear the guilty, visiting the
iniquity of the fathers on the children
and the children's children to the third
and fourth generation.
>> Okay. So, yeah, everything you said is
right. There's something that we do um
in therapy and um it's called a gog and
it's it's really just it's basically
going through it's like basically a
family tree. So, we're taking three
generations. So, say somebody comes in
and says, "Hey, I'm dealing with this,
this, and this." I'm like, "Okay, I want
to get a family assessment, but not just
the current family, but I want to go up
three generations." Why do I want to go
up three generations? Because you can
find patterns of behavior and issues
through looking um three generations up.
I mean, you can probably go four
generations, but we do three three
generations up because
>> if um
>> you can see if the that the grandfather
had, you know, was an alcoholic, right?
And so, and then but he was abused as a
child or whatever. So, these different
things um can be translated to some of
his children that are causing some of
the same issues. And you're able to see,
you're able to map things out and make
it shorter. You're able to map it out
and even show the client how this
behavior that they're doing now was like
gone up like let's say three
generations, but you're also able to
help them show how they can break that
negative uh behavior so that it's not
passing on to their children and deal
with their current issue.
>> Yeah. So generational sins do impact
the
generations after them just because
they're taking that bad behavior. So I'm
going to say it's like genetic like oh
you're born with this sin because you're
it's behaviors that they learn once
they're here.
>> Generational sins are not are not
genetic. They are
>> they are learned behaviors.
>> It's learned behavior.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So like their mom acted that
way because her mom acted that way. And
so now she's acting that way with you
and you're responding, you know, and
maybe by the third generation, they're
like, you know, maybe I want to go to
therapy and start deal you're it's
learned behavior.
>> It's learned behavior. And um you know
that that's uh
yeah
>> that can that's and whether it's
generational I mean like that in itself
I think that understanding helps us to
be like well you know what I got to
realize that my my behavior doesn't just
impact me
>> it can set the path for my children.
>> Oh yeah
>> and their children
>> and their children.
>> Right.
>> Yeah. And the same thing with healthy
uh behaviors. So like if of course you
have parents that are
>> um treating you in a healthy way and all
the you know if your environment is good
growing up all these things then you can
pass that along as well. So it's not
just the
>> the bad negative things.
>> So yeah. Mhm.
>> So, that's all the time for today for
our questions, but please tune in next
week when we're going to answer
>> uh some of the questions that we didn't
get to and new questions as well. So,
that would be fun.
>> Amen.
>> Yes. Do you want to talk about your
sermon?
>> Uh so, uh my sermon is actually going to
be uh it's called the Mount of Curses.
And um I've preached on this um before
uh for living mana, but not in uh I've
talked about these. I'm not going to say
anything else. Make sure you tune in.
>> Just know he never even if he's never
going to preach anything the same way,
guys. So
>> yeah, make sure you tune in for
>> Don't think you've heard it because you
haven't heard it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And um yeah, Atante, they
were saying that your mic, you know,
>> you know what? I It might have been
because I was sitting back and not I was
not so close to the mic. I hope that's
better.
>> Yeah,
that should be better.
>> I hope it's better.
>> And just just know this, you know, Atant
and I are I I'm the introvert. She's the
extrovert. So when we share and when we
talk, listen y'all.
>> Don't be
>> I love you, husband. Yeah,
>> I knew you were gonna say something. I
know you so well.
>> When you know, listen, I I will be
quiet. When it's time for me to preach,
I I'm preaching. But the way we talk and
whatever,
>> I'm not here to interrupt him.
>> She she'll jump in and say stuff and I
you know what we just we just kind of
roll like that. So uh just you know just
know
>> welcome into our life.
>> Well yeah
>> this is how we talk.
>> This is how we talk.
>> And uh when it's time for me to preach
y'all I preach.
>> I'm silent.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Anyways, no this was a blessing. We
look forward to answering your questions
next week. And um you want to you did do
your sermon. Okay. All right. So, we're
going to close in prayer. Don't go
anywhere.
Share, like, subscribe, invite. Invite,
guys. Invite. Invite your friends and
family to church. They're not going to
want to miss. They've already missed a
blessing. I mean, they could have had
some of their biblical and mental health
questions answered, but you could invite
them for next week. Yeah. And tell them
that they can do the same. So, uh,
definitely invite, uh, your friends to
church. And if you have not liked or
subscribed, please do. Living Mana took
a big jump. Like, I think I saw we're at
11,000 and something subscribers. So,
that's great. So, keep doing that. Let's
keep it growing.
>> Yeah. And you know what? I think I might
come back to that to that DNA because
some people are like, I inherited some
stuff. There is inherited and cultivated
sins. And maybe we might talk about that
next week to kind of fill in on that
answer. But um
>> okay, since we're here and we not left
yet and we haven't prayed, let me just
say this. So to that like um I like the
way it was described. I don't know where
I learned this from, but um it was
described. It's almost like like um
it's just like you could have a genetic
thing to have diabetes or some health
issue, right?
>> So it's like it's a loaded gun, but a
gun doesn't go off unless you pull the
trigger.
>> So you if you're
>> you may have a disposition.
>> Yes. A disposition. Yeah.
>> But you don't have to. And and so a lot
of behaviors are so you might already
have the disposition and if if your
environment is cultivating that
disposition to have some of the very
same bad behavior that was in the
generation before from one of your
parents or something then that's like
pulling the trigger.
>> Yeah. Um, but if you put you could have,
let's just say adopted children, like
their biological parents could have had
a disposition and genetics to, you know,
their the
the gun is loaded, but because they're
raised in a different environment and a
healthy environment,
>> it the trigger wasn't pulled.
>> Yeah. which actually goes right back to
Jesus who was born with uh like us,
right? He had the capacity to sin but
never pulled the trigger.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely.
>> Right. So you look at Jesus lineage and
you know who is in his
>> who he comes from. I mean
>> there were some bad folks. There was
some bad folks.
>> Yep. It wasn't a which incidentally is
one of the reasons why the Catholic
Church teaches the immaculate conception
which is not that Jesus was immaculately
conceived but Mary was immaculately
conceived so that Jesus could be born
with a nature different from ours in a
sense that this is why he didn't sin.
>> Yes. Right.
>> Okay. And the more you go back, if if
Mary was immaculately conceived, then
that you know, if we're following the
logic, then her mother would have been
had to been have been immaculately
conceived. Her parents,
>> um Jesus was born. Uh he was made in the
likeness of sinful flesh,
>> but he never pulled the trigger.
>> Right? And that's the difference. We
pulled the trigger. Jesus didn't pull
the trigger.
So
>> sometimes we're in environments that
we're not gonna be able to say cause us
to pull the trigger.
>> We're not gonna be able to say our
parents made us do this.
>> Yeah. No.
>> Yeah.
>> Um thank you fellow mental health coun
uh profession professional because I
said I work in addictions as an
addiction counselor. Many individuals
believe that addictions are genetic. Let
me get close to the mic. But we have no
evidence. Most individuals grow up in
the environment that cultivates the
addiction.
>> Yeah,
>> absolutely.
>> All right.
>> Thank you.
>> That was a detour, but
>> what he or she said.
>> Amen. Amen. All right. So, we're going
to pray and uh we'll continue on with
the worship service.
>> Yes. Please invite.
>> Please invite. And
>> we have lots of fun here.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Amen. Let's pray. Heavenly
Father, thank you for speaking to us
today. Thank you Lord for your word, for
your love for us. And Lord, as we
continue our worship today, Lord, we
pray that it will be acceptable in your
sight. Um Lord, please bless this
message that is coming up, the mount of
curses. And Lord, may it speak to to the
people who who will be hearing it for
the first time, Lord. Um thank you
again, Lord, for all that you do for us
and for your love towards us, Lord. Um
bless us as we continue to worship as
our prayer in Jesus name. Amen.
>> Amen.
on the west side of the big island of
Hawaii is a small town that's known for
a lot of amazing things. Kyuakona is a
land of black lava fields, rugged rocky
coastlines, crystal clear waters,
historical Hawaiian howls, fruitful fish
ponds, and ancient petetroglyphs. It is
the home of the iconic Kona coffee bean,
the annual Iron Man triathlon, the
international billfish deep water
fishing tournament, and so much more.
But of all the things that Kona is
famous for, none is more awe inspiring
than what you're able to see just after
sunset, just below the surface of the
ocean.
As the sun slips below the western
horizon, it's time for us to slip
beneath the surface of the water. And as
you sink into the black water below,
it's like being transported into another
planet. It is like descending into the
dark abyss of a whole new world. It is
dark, but it's anything but dreary or
dull. For below the surface of the black
knight is what I consider one of the top
five things to see before you die. Giant
manta rays dancing in the nightlight.
Considered by many as one of the best
night dives in the world, the Blackwater
Manta dive is an experience that no
human language can adequately describe.
You got to see it to believe it.
All year long, these massive manta ray
with wingspans of up to 15 ft long glide
through the coastal waters with mouths
wide open. They are filter feeders
feasted upon large quantities of zup
plankton in the form of shrimp, krill,
and tiny crabs. With their broad heads,
triangular wing-like pectoral fins,
hornlike syphalic fins, flat disc-like
bodies, and wide mouths. They are an
incredible sight to behold. As the manta
approaches the cloud of plankton, it
unrolls its syphalic fins in order to
channel the food into their mouths. As
the cloud of plankton is particularly
thick, the mantle will do somersaults or
barrel rolls to catch all the tiny
critters. And even though the opening of
their mouths can fit your head, these
magnificent creatures are perfectly
harmless. They don't have any teeth,
their esophagus is about the size of a
small coin. And unlike their stingray
cousins, manta rays do not have the
barbed tail stinger. They're
non-aggressive and perfectly harmless to
humans. It was an awesome privilege to
be in the presence of these gentle
giants of the sea as they did their mant
dance in the bright night light.
The reason why the blackwater manta dive
is one of the best night dives in the
world is because the mantas are drawn to
the light. The light attracts the
plankton, the plankton attracts the
mantas, and the mantas attract happy
divers like me. It's a win-win situation
for the mantas and the divers. The
mantas get a good meal, and the divers
get an unforgettable show. Flashlights
are provided by the dive company. But
tonight, I brought my own dive light,
which happens to be 10 times brighter
than all the rest. And since the mantas
are attracted to the light, whoever has
the brightest light becomes the most
attractive. Words kind of describe the
feeling I had. Seeing manta after manta
come to me with wingspans up to 15 ft
long and mouths wide open, doing barrel
rolls over my head all dive long. Some
got so close that their tummies were
rubbing on the top of my head. It was
nothing short of spectacular.
Besides the experience itself, the
spiritual lesson the mantis taught was
just as incredible. You see, as the
mant's hunger is fulfilled by coming
close to the light, so too the longing
heart of humanity can only be satisfied
in the light of God's love. It is in the
illuminating light of God's love that we
experience the fullness of joy and
pleasures forever more. The love of God
is the brightest light in the universe
that attracts hungry humanity from the
darkness of death and into the light of
life. Jesus said, "I am the light of the
world. He that follows me shall not walk
in darkness, but shall have the light of
life." And it was said of him that in
him was life, and the life was the light
of man, and the light shines in the
darkness, and the darkness comprehended
it not. You see, in a world full of
dense spiritual darkness, deception,
distraction, delusion, and destruction,
we must come close to the nightlight. We
must look upon and listen to the light
of God's word. For thy word is a lamp
unto my feet and a light unto my path.
And the entrance of thy words gives
light. It gives understanding to the
simple. And as we come to dwell in the
light of truth and love, we then become
lamps to shine that same light to those
around us. And he who has the brightest
light becomes the most attractive. For
the Bible says, for God who commanded
the light to shine out of darkness has
shined in our hearts to give the light
of the knowledge of the glory of God in
the face of Jesus Christ. But we have
this treasure in earthn vessels that the
excellency of the power may be of God
and not of us. Jesus is the light and he
makes us his lamp to shine his light of
love in a world of spiritual darkness.
So in these last days as the son of hope
gives way to the night of woe, I invite
you to come to the nightlight. When the
darkness of the evil and settles all
around you and you feel all alone, come
to the nightlight. When the night of
sorrow is long and the day of joy short,
come to the bright night light, learn
the lessons from the mant dance. Open
your mouth wide so that God can fill it.
And when you do, just like the mantas of
the Kona cos, people will flock to see
the one that is shining in and through
your life. The wonderful God of grace
who teaches us to dance like the mantas
in the glorious gleaming of the bright
nightlight.
Heat. Heat.
Heat. Heat. Heat.
Heat. Heat. N.
Heat. Heat.
Heat.
Heat up
here.
Heat. Heat.
Li
well hi guys. Hi, welcome back. I wanted
to say welcome back Living Mana Church
family and like the living mana part was
coming out of my mouth before the
welcome but welcome back guys. So happy
to see you here. Uh you decided to
continue to worship with us. So we just
are thankful that you are here
worshiping with us on this the Sabbath
day. If you did not put in the chat
where you're viewing from and you're new
just joining us now for the divine
worship service, please put in the chat,
put your name, put where you're viewing
from. And if this is your very first
time worshiping with Living Manage
Church, we want to say a special welcome
to you and let you know just a little
bit about uh Living Manage Church. And
we are happy to see all of you here
today. Uh Sabbath school was a
refreshing blessing. I mean, it's always
a blessing, but we did something a
little bit different. Did something that
we used to do doing the question and
answers. And it was enjoyable to answer
some of your mental health questions and
to hear pastor's answers to some of your
biblical questions. And as you know, we
said we're going to be back next week
doing that, too. And then we will
continue on with our uh Christian Art of
War series because that is absolutely
amazing. Love to do that with our panel
as well. So, I want to say welcome and
happy Sabbath to Wendy who is viewing
from Idaho. It is very good to have you
here. Uh Wendy um here at Living Mana
Church. And again, if this is your very
first time, just want to let people know
that you can uh put in the chat that a
one. There we go. We got a one. All
right. And um I think that's Rey. I
don't know if that's your name. I'm just
looking at the handle. Um we have
another one. Okay, we have a couple of
ones. Praise the Lord. We you are we are
so happy that you are here worshiping
with us today. We are living manage
church is a 100% online church. Our
viewership and membership is all around
the world all around the globe
everywhere. And we um are just so
thankful for that. But we're thankful
that you are here. Please ones if you
don't mind please tell us where you're
viewing from. We'd love to see that as
well.
But we are completely online church. We
are here Sabbath. Um and we have church
service. We have um Sabbath school which
was just the last program that we just
came out of. We have programs all
throughout the week. We have mental
health uh programs on on Monday. And
that's hosted by myself. I'm a licensed
marriage and family therapist and Dr.
Ricardo White who is a psychiatrist. We
both um host mental health Mondays. We
also have True Health Tuesdays which is
currently being hosted by Maria Humel
who is um she is a licensed nutritionist
um and she's actually Dr. Maria so
excuse me for that. Um and we have and
she's teaching us amazing things about
health and you not you're definitely
going to want to tune in for that. Um
and then we have our prayer services on
on Wednesday. Okay. So, we have two
prayer services and you're going to
learn more about that here in just a few
moments as I'm doing the announcements.
On Thursdays, we have pastor, our young
adult pastor, uh, Pastor Lwami
Richardson has a program as well. So, as
you can see, we're here all throughout
the week. It's not just Sabbath. We
actually have a lot of small groups that
you might be interested in looking at.
And again, I'll tell you how you can do
that um here in just a moment during the
announcement time. But again, just
welcome. We are happy to have all of our
first timers, our ones here with us. But
while I was doing that, I missed to say
welcome to some of you. So, we have um
we have nurse Sandy is here from
Florida. Welcome, nurse Sandy. Um and
Rey, it's you're you're viewing from
Canada. Um Calgary, Canada. I've been
there. Super cold. I was there. We were
there I think in January, so that's why
it was so cold. But it was so so cold. I
remember. But yes, but Canada is a
beautiful country. Um, and Rachel,
you're saying that you are viewing from
Trinidad and you're a one. This is your
first time. So, welcome here to Living
Mana Church. We are so happy to have all
of you. Um, and then we have MacArthur
from southeastern Ohio. Welcome. Good to
see you here at Living Mana Church. Oh,
and somebody is watching from the
beautiful city of Santa Barbara,
California. And I say that because I am
a California native and I was born only
about an hour and a half from Santa
maybe not. Yeah, about an hour and a
half from Santa Barbara. So, welcome. Um
who um from those who are watching in
Santa Barbara, it's good to have you
here.
And we have uh Little Rock, Arkansas.
Welcome. Good to see you guys here. you
know, just to let you guys know um how
to stay connected to Living Mana Church
all uh throughout the week, just all the
time, I want to show you how to do that.
So, our first timers, you're going to
really want to pay attention to to this
information. So, if you want to be
reminded and get text alerts when Living
Mana Church is going live or other um
information and announcements that
Living Mana Church may have, you're
going to want to sign up for text
alerts. And you are able to do that by
texting LMOC to that 855 number that you
see on the screen. And that will uh send
you the prompts to complete to be
getting signed up so that you can get
those text alerts and be reminded and
stay connected to LMOC and to to always
know what we are doing. Um and so that
if you have time and are interested, you
can pop on and join us. That's how you
stay connected. If you're here in
America, as I said, we are an
international church, so we have viewers
viewing viewership from all around the
world. And so text the LMC text the 855
number won't work if you're not in
America. Um, but what does work is you
should sign up for Mighty Network. And
that's for everybody. Whether you're in
America or if you're somewhere somewhere
around the world, you want to sign up
for Mighty Networks because that is our
virtual church home. We are a church
without walls but that doesn't mean we
don't have a home. We have a home and
our virtual home is on mighty networks
and that is where community is formed
here on u for living mana church. That
is where you'll get to learn about all
the different small groups that we have.
You can meet the leaders of the small
group. You can meet other church members
view an audience and get to know people
better in mighty networks. And the link
to Mighty Networks is in the chat. So,
you're going to want to uh sign up for
that if you want to be connected and
stay connected to Living Mana Church.
We also have a kids ministry and that is
Elosi Kids and they are learning amazing
things at Lamosci Kids. They're learning
a lot of things that we're teaching here
for adults, but they're learning on a
kids level. And so I just got a report
like last week on on what the kids are
learning and what they're sharing. And
it's pretty amazing. Like if you were
impressed with the youth last week, you
would be very impressed with what the
young kids are learning as well. So, if
you want to sign uh your kids up or a
grandchild or a niece or a nephew or if
you're an auntie or an uncle, you can uh
text kids to that 855 number or you can
send an email to the leadership team um
for LMOC kids at living.urch
and that's how you can get your kids
involved with living manaurch. Also want
to remind everyone that Pastor Meyers
does have virtual church office hours.
So if you are needing to connect with
the pastor, you can make an appointment
uh by uh sending an email to patrice at
living manana.live and she will set that
appointment up for you. If you are
interested in becoming a member of
living manaurch, there's three different
ways that you can do that. You can
transfer your membership if you're a
seventh if you're already a 7th Day
Adventist member. at another Seventh Day
Adventist Church, you can have your
membership transferred. If you um do not
have membership at a 7th Day Adventist
Church, but you've already been baptized
and you're a Christian and you want to
join Living Man Church, you can join by
profession of faith. And if you want to
be baptized, you can be baptized into
the Seventh Day Adventist Church, but
your church would be Living Manit
Church, and Pastor Meyers will baptize
you. So, if you want to do either three
of those things that I just mentioned,
you can send an email to patrice
livingmana.live and she will get that
started for you.
Also want to remind you guys about the
power the prayer power line that's on
Wednesday and that is on YouTube. Um,
and that's at 8:00 PM central right
after our power Wednesday uh prayer
service. And so the power line is really
a wonderful way to uh just to share and
invite people to um our church but
through prayer because we pray for the
prayer requests that come up in the chat
right then and there. So it's s it's
just prayer. So, if you have a family
member or for yourself or a co-orker or
if you're just you're needing prayer and
you want to, you know, get to be prayed
for right then and there, you're going
to want to visit the power line and
invite other people uh to come as well.
Or just let them know and say, "Hey, I'm
going to take your prayer request in
your situation. Uh I'm going to take it
to the power line and my church is going
to pray uh for you." And um it's a great
way to just share u about living mana
church but just about the power of God
and prayer and what God can do. So we're
very thankful and and very excited about
what the power line is doing on YouTube.
Okay. We have uh a business directory uh
as a church. So it's um a business
directory and you can see the email
there. Um, but just to tell you a little
bit more about it, a living mana
business uh resource directory is now
available within the mighty networks
platform under give mana. Church members
and friends who own a business are
invited to submit their listings by
emailing and you can see the email there
on your screen. So send an email that
you see there with your full name,
business name, and phone number.
Also want to let you guys know and we
have a video that's going to talk about
it about Hangouts and what Hangouts is
doing in the month of November.
Greetings living mana. How are you? So
good to see you. Okay, here's my
question.
What dish is it that you really, really
want this Thanksgiving 2025?
Mac and cheese, the healthy style. What
is it?
Let us know. Visit us on Mighty Network.
And please don't forget to join Hangout
so we can hang out and discuss your
favorite dish. Can't wait to see you.
God bless.
Hello, my living mana family. Um, for
this Thanksgiving, I'm looking forward
to eating my regular um macaroni pie,
also known as mac and cheese, um, potato
salad, and roast cone. That's it.
Hey everybody,
it's Thomas here.
What's my favorite dish
I'm looking forward to for this
Thanksgiving?
I gota say that's a hard one because
there are so many.
I would say after
little bit of deliberation,
it's going to have to be the candy jams.
Yep. Yep.
to me. All the nice seasonings on there,
spices, cinnamon, nutmeg, all that
butter. Um, and yeah, then layer that
stuff with
uh marshmallows. So, I use dandies,
right?
Yeah, it's good stuff.
And then also
looking forward to spending time with
family.
And that's it. All right, y'all. Take
care.
>> Hello. Hello, Loc family. This is Takara
here. Um, I am excited about
Thanksgiving. It's also one of my
favorite holidays coming up, spending
time with family. A new thing for me is
that I'm going to make is the purple
sweet potato pie. I love sweet potato
pie. My mother is known for making her
sweet potato pie, which is, you know,
you're using the regular yams or the
regular sweet potatoes. But this time, I
am deciding to try out a new dessert,
which I love is the purple sweet potato.
It looks fancy on your table. It's a
beautiful light lavender purple. I'll
probably post a picture of it, but that
is what I'm excited about. So, soon
coming up is our Thanksgiving holiday.
So, I hope everyone is um excited as I
am about Thanksgiving. Have a blessed
one.
that I don't know if that if that if
you're not hungry watching that you
should you I'm surprised because I'm
hungry and I'll just say that I'm
looking forward to having pastor Myers
Kentucky fried tofu for um for
Thanksgiving and it's it tastes like
chicken, looks like chicken, but it's
not chicken. It's it's great. And so I'm
looking forward to that. But I also want
to let you guys know some other things
that Hangouts is doing because the whole
month of November,
um they are previewing the latest season
of the thrilling series House of David.
uh we'll watch the show together and
afterwards uh they'll share uh insights
and critique as hangouts crew we worship
together. Let's watch House of David
together. So if you can also text uh
Hangouts to the 855 number for reminders
so you don't miss the show. Scan the QR
code to join the Hangout space in Mighty
Network. Sounds like a lot of fun guys.
Don't don't miss it. Um, people always
say, "How can you as an online church do
social things and be connected?" This is
one of the ways we can hang out and
watch uh biblical uh movies together and
just hang out and have fun. And I can
tell you I've attended them and they are
lots of fun. What else want to also
remind you guys about our digital small
groups. Whether you're carrying a fresh
vision for a small group or simply uh
longing for deeper connection, our
digital digital small groups ministry is
the place to start. We believe
transformation happens in community.
Have a small group idea? We'd love to
hear it and help you bring it to life.
Looking to join a group? There's a space
waiting for you. Whether you're
passionate about Bible study, creative
disciplehip, or connecting with others
uh who share your favorite hobbies,
we've got a space for you. Our community
is hosted on mighty networks where you
can connect anytime, anywhere. It's more
than a platform. It's a movement of
believers growing together in faith,
purpose, and love. Check out today and
find your your pe your people. your next
step starts here. So, um definitely if
you are interested in that, get started.
You can send an email uh to that email
that you see there on the screen. Also
want to let you guys know what Jim is up
to. Uh Gyms is a small is a small group
ministry. In every season of faith, we
need people who walk with us, not just
ahead of us, but beside us. That's the
heart of GEMS, a digital small group
where mature Christians come alongside
u the new believers to offer
encouragement, wisdom, and spirit-led
mentorship. Whether you're just
beginning your journey or you've been
walking with Christ for years, Gyms is a
space honest questions, practical
growth, and deep spiritual connection.
We believe disciplehip is rel relational
and transformative happens when we share
life together.
New to faith, you'll find guidance,
grace, and a safe place to grow.
Seasonal believer, your experience can
help um or I should say, I'm sorry,
seasoned believer, not seasonal. None of
us need to be seasonal believer. Uh but
a seasoned believer, your experience can
help shape someone's future in Christ.
Join us on Mighty Networks and discover
a community committed to growing in
love, truth, and purpose, one
conversation at a time. So, that's an
amazing group as well. And if you are
interested, please um text gems to that
855 number that you see on your screen.
Wanted to tell you guys about Star the
Addiction
doesn't get the final word. God does.
The Star Group is a digital small group
for anyone seeking recovery, healing,
and hope. Whether you're walking through
substance recovery, breaking patterns of
emotional dependency, or navigating any
form of addiction, Star is a safe place
to grow in grace and truth. Here, mature
believers walk alongside you, not to fix
you, but to support you. We believe in
the power of accountability, prayer, and
spirit-led renewal. You don't have to
walk alone. Healing happens in
community. And Star is built to be that
place of refuge and restoration. Join us
in mighty networks and take your next
step toward freedom. Star isn't just a
group, it's a lifeline. You're not
alone. Let's walk let's walk this out
together. And so if you're interested,
definitely um again text star to that
855 number and you can see there that
star meets Sundays at 11 central time.
Okay. Well, I want to just let you guys
know about LMLC Global. And for those
who have not um or that are just
learning about it for the first time,
just going to show you a little snippet
of what that looks like. Ghost.
foreign
Fore!
Foreign! Foreign!
New York
go.
For those of you who are seeing this for
the first time, you're probably thinking
like, "Man, I didn't know Pastor Myers
could speak Japanese." Well, he cannot
speak Japanese. But uh we are able
currently to translate uh his sermons
into seven different languages, and
Japanese is just one of them. So, if uh
we would like for you to visit LMLC
Global um on our you on on our YouTube
channel so you can see the seven
different languages and to see the
messages that are are there currently.
And if you speak that language or if you
know someone who speaks that language
that you'd like to share some of his
videos with, please do that. Please uh
take a look at our LMLC Global YouTube
channel to see what uh languages that
are there and available. Um because you
never know your the language that you
want to share with someone that uh
speaks maybe only Spanish and you think
that uh having the message delivered in
their language would be more beneficial
uh you definitely can go there and
choose some of the messages again that
are already on that channel. If you
would like to support Living Mana Global
you can do that by going to
adventistgiving.org.
Um, and there if you put in LMLC church,
you will see a tithe envelope come down
and you'll see many different areas that
you can support. You can give your tithe
which goes to the Northeastern
Conference. Living Mana Church is a
Northeastern Conference church and you
can see the local church budget that
helps us to be able to do all the things
that Living Mana Church is doing all
around the world. Uh, because we are an
international church. Um, and so as you
can see, we're online. So we have to get
equipment to be able to provide quality
online programming. And so when you give
to uh our local church budget that helps
to do that as well and many other things
you will see that you there's a
benevolence fund that you can give to as
well that helps to provide um funds or
different things for people that are in
need when they reach out to the church.
And again you'll see all the different
categories when you go to
adventistgiving.org
org and put in LivingMana Church. If you
don't want to give online, but you would
like to mail in your um tithe or
offering, you are able to do that by
using the address that that is there on
your screen. And that is PO Box 428,
Owens Crossroads, Alabama 35763.
Please put a note uh when you send um
your your love gift to a living man
church to let us know if it's for tithe,
for offering, for benevolence fund, uh
LMLC global or another area that you
would like to support. So, we just want
to say thank you to all of you for
supporting this church and this
ministry. Uh we will be four years old
on April 9th. I know that's still a
little bit of ways away, but we're still
just blown away about what God is able
to do and what he has done with Living
Mana Church. And it is because of your
faithfulness and and giving your
continual giving to Living Mana Church
to support uh this church and to go into
all the world. And so again, we just
want to say thank you and we want to say
thank you to God and just lift a prayer
of thanksgiving to him at this time. So,
if you would please just bow your heads
with me as we pray.
Heavenly Father, Lord, I just thank you
for this Sabbath. Lord, I thank you for
uh the study that we had during Sabbath
school, just answering those questions
that are on the hearts and minds of your
children, Lord. Um I'm looking forward
to what you have given Pastor Meyers to
bless us with uh today in the sermon.
And Lord, I want to just lift up every
single person that is here. You know
exactly what's going on in their life.
You know if they barely made it to
church today. You know what happened
during the week. You know their needs,
health, financial, family, what it could
be mental health. Lord, you know what's
going on in their life. And I just pray
over them asking that you would bring
healing into their life. Bring peace
into their life. Show them that you are
here for them and that you are on the
case and you are working things out.
maybe not the way that they originally
prayed it, but the way that's best for
them and the situation. Help them to
trust you and to have faith. And Lord,
again, we just pray for Pastor Meyers as
we know you have given him a message for
us today. And we just ask that the Holy
Spirit would bring it to our hearts and
touch our hearts the way that you want
us to be moved. and that we we will
change that we will uh not leave church
today the same way that we came in and
allow you to work on our hearts and and
make a miracle uh cause a miracle to
come out of that. Lord, we thank you for
just for this Sabbath and just being
you, God. We praise you in Jesus name.
Amen.
to continue
on February.
Oh, that's
seriously
Okay.
Oh,
where is it all going? Please, please,
please.
Why is this happening?
No,
>> it's 1278.
>> All right, let me get your uh
No, buddy. No, no, buddy. No, no, buddy.
>> Hey, honey. Are you taking things for
granted again?
Yeah,
I guess so.
>> All right. Well, is there anything you
can do about that? Because we really
need to do some laundry.
>> Laura, will you please give me a more
grateful heart?
>> Honey, my car.
Okay.
Yeah.
They say this mountain can't be moved.
They say these chains will never break.
But they don't know you like we do.
There is power in your name.
We've heard that there is no way
through.
We've heard the tide will never change.
They haven't seen what you can do.
There is power in your name.
So much power in your name.
Move the unmovable.
Break the unbreakable.
God we believe.
God we believe for it. from the
impossible.
Who will see a miracle?
God, we believe.
God, we believe for it.
We know that hope is never lost.
For there is still an empty grave.
God we believe no matter what
there is power in your name.
So much power in your name.
Move the unmovable.
Break the unbreakable.
God, we believe.
God, we believe. For it. From the
impossible.
We'll see your miracle.
God, we believe.
God, we believe for it. You are the way
where there seems to be no way.
We trust in you, God. You have the final
say,
you are the way where there seems to be
no way.
We trust in you, God. You have the final
faith.
Yeah.
Move the unmovable.
Break the unbreakable.
God we believe.
God we believe for it from the
impossible.
We'll see a miracle.
God we believe.
God we believe for it. Move the
unmovable.
Break the unbreakable.
God, we believe.
God, we believe for it. From the
impossible.
We see a miracle.
God, we believe.
God, we believe for it.
You said it, we believe it. You said it,
it is done.
You said it and we believe it. You said
it. It is done.
You said it. We believe it. You said it.
It is done.
You said it. We believe that you said
it. It is love.
Move the unmovable.
Break the unbreakable.
God, we believe.
God, we believe for it. From the
impossible,
we'll see a miracle.
God, we believe.
God, we believe. For it. Move the
unmovable.
Break the unbreakable.
God we believe.
God we believe for it from the
impossible.
We'll see your miracle.
God we believe.
God we believe forever from the
impossible.
We'll see your miracle.
God we believe.
God, we believe forever. God, we
believe.
God, we believe.
God, we believe forever.
Here at Living Mana, we bear each
other's burdens. When you need support
or prayer, when you're feeling
discouraged
or alone or anxious,
you don't have to face life struggles
alone.
Let us come boldly unto the throne of
grace that we may obtain mercy and find
grace to help in our time of need.
The Lord is close to the brokenhearted
and saves those who are crushed in
spirit.
Greetings saints of the most high God.
Welcome to another edition of living
mana's prayer and praise time. I am
brother Terry here with my lovely bride
Amra as always. Hello everyone. Living
man of family everywhere everywhere
you're watching from. You know I was
excited this morning looking when first
lady came on and she began to greet
people from everywhere. Something has
happened with YouTube. Everybody's
handles are kind of changed a little
bit. So, we kind of get those names
mixed up. They're mixed with numbers and
stuff. But look, people were Before I do
that, look, I don't want to take
anything for granted. I love the bumper
video on Be Thankful, right?
>> It kind of reminded me, you you know,
some of you who listen to me all the
time telling my story and give my
testimony. I always talk about vacation,
right? Because that was a time where God
had me in a season where I had
absolutely nothing but God. And just for
those viewers who don't know what
vacation means, he means prison. He was
in prison, which does not sound like a
vacation to me,
>> you know. And I thank God. God will give
you a wife if you need one that'll
always come and explain what you're
talking about. I was talking. They know.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Thank you, honey. I need
>> We had some ones in the chat earlier, so
maybe some not everyone knew, but
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Go ahead.
>> If you're here for the first time, put a
one in the chat. We want to greet you
and say hello and and we love you.
Welcome to Living Mana. If you ever hear
Brother Terry talking about vacation,
he's talking about prison. But I want to
get to the point here. The reason why I
always mention that is not because I
want everybody to know my story and my
business and stuff, but I want you to be
encouraged that if God would show his
love and compassion and mercy for
someone like I used to be, then he will
do it for you. And that's why I always
want to share it because if you think
you're in a rough situation, you think
you're in a rough place in life and a
rough season, God's not hearing my cry.
Yes, he does. He hear the prisoner in
the prison house bring him from the dung
hill, bring him from the pit, bring him
from the bottom, transform and change
him and put him where he wants him to
be. And so, listen saints, be encouraged
today.
>> And then the psalmist said, I will enter
his uh gates with thanksgiving in my
heart. I'll enter his courtroom with
praise. Our song used to say, "I will
say this is the day the Lord hath made.
I will rejoice for he hath made me
glad." And so, let's take a moment
living manner and just say, "Thank you,
Lord." Look, I don't want my dog
disappearing. I don't want my lawnmower
disappearing. I don't want my stuff
disappearing. I don't want to take
anything for granted because God is
good. Can we say amen in that chat right
now together? We're worshiping. Come on,
somebody say, "Thank you, Jesus." Thank
you, Jesus, for everything you have
done.
>> Amen. Hallelujah.
>> It's so hard to believe that
Thanksgiving in the States is next week
already.
>> Yes,
>> we just had a 100 degree temperature not
too long ago. So, it's just the holidays
just creep on by and here they are.
>> But it's so important to be thankful
every day. Absolutely. Every day.
>> Look, I know everybody's been saying
that, you know, it looks like the time
is just flying by, but it's not. It just
seems that way. But we won't allow that
to cause us not to be thankful. Not to
be thankful. That's right, Zadina.
>> I used to call it that, too.
>> She says, "I I call prison college."
State state uh uh what is it? College
State pen.
>> Yeah, it was that. Believe me. Yes, it
was definitely a college for me because
at the feet of Jesus there, I learned so
much. I became a man there, by the way.
and um became a man of God and became a
brother, became a servant, became uh
just everything I am and all I have is
mine only because I am in Christ Jesus
today. And so I can't be thankful
enough. Thank uh Living Manographics
team for sharing that video. That video
was something else. Simple, but it made
it happen. And so I am thankful and I'm
thankful for all of you, my family.
Y'all are here. And uh I praise God for
y'all. Some of y'all were praying for
me, didn't even know me. You were
praying for me and God was hearing your
prayers and answering. So, thank you so
much. Look, let me just do this. Linda
Kingsdale, you sent us a message from
Holland. A blesses blessing this morning
from Holland of all places. Beautiful
Holland. Beautiful Linda, God bless you.
Thank you for that blessing. Eastern
Europe, we got yours. Barbados, I know
our sister blessing is there. Sister
Blessing, you better come on here and be
a blessing to us one day. Come on with
us from uh Barbados. Um, Tanzania,
Vancouver. We know our sister Jod's
there.
>> South Africa. Love y'all. Y'all send
some good blessings from South Africa.
Uh, we we definitely remember uh who in
South Africa was asking for revival.
>> Uh, Nambia. Y'all are asking for revi
revival there in in Walus Bay. So, we're
going to be praying for y'all about
that.
>> Was Bay. Nambia.
>> That's right. Nambia. Love y'all.
Portuguese is here and Gilla is here.
Michigan, United States of America.
Michigan, we shouting out y'all today.
Australia's in the house. Minnesota,
Spokane, Washington, I believe. We got
some family up there in Spokane. Uh,
Sister Crystal's up there. Ross and
Gina's up there in Washington. So, we
love y'all. Love y'all. And
>> hello, Nicole. Hello, Jamie. Hello,
Ashley Owens.
>> What just happened in here?
>> And rain. That Okay, you may spell your
name R A Y N E, but my mother's name is
Rain. R A I N E.
>> Amen.
>> And I used to have a middle name, Rain,
but now it's my main name.
>> And by the way, that little roll call
just rained on my shout outs, too.
>> Oh, I'm sorry.
>> That's all right, though. See how the
roll call just happened.
>> Money P6026.
Thank you so much.
>> Bless you right back, sister.
Hallelujah.
>> I'm sorry. I could I just I couldn't
help it. I couldn't help it.
>> Hey, do what you do. We love it. Uh the
praises go up in this place. We love
y'all. We family. Listen, I took Emma
her home a little while ago, right? To
South Carolina. Speaking of Carolina,
Greenville, North Carolina's in the
house today. Love y'all. Shout out to
y'all. New Jersey, don't think we forgot
you. We saw you. So, speaking of
Carolina, took Amber home and she found
out how we do it in our culture, right?
Everybody in the house, everybody
talking all at one time. Loud.
>> I love it.
>> And laughing.
>> I felt like I fit right at the same
time.
>> I felt like I fit right.
>> You did. You did. That's what I was too.
So,
>> that was the point. She fit right in. I
was like, "Okay, there they go." So,
praise God everybody. Shouting y'all out
and love y'all today. If I didn't
mention your name specifically, look
everybody, y'all thoughts, y'all names
are just going through my head today.
And I love y'all living man of family.
We love y'all. We're We are humbly uh
grateful
to be a part of what's going on here,
man. When we get to glory, what a time
it's going to be.
>> Can we just think a moment here and just
look forward to glory?
>> Absolutely. My my my Thank you, Jesus.
Thank you, Jesus, for bringing us
through. Glory. Glory. Raleigh, North
Carolina is here today. My sisters in
South Carolina, whether I see y'all or
not, uh, want to shout y'all out.
Everybody in the Carolinas, that's home.
Love
>> Minnesota. We got Greenville,
Spartanberg.
>> Oh, wait a minute. They all in the
Carolinas putting them out there. That's
right. We I know Greenville,
Spartanberg.
>> Hopefully, we'll get out there soon.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Okay. So,
>> oh, and Bri, of course, who I got to
meet,
>> you know, Sister Bri is in North
Carolina.
>> Yes. I got to meet her a couple years
ago on a work trip. It was so awesome to
meet her and her kids. We still have the
the little pictures that her children
drew us on our refrigerator.
>> Sitting right there on the refrigerator.
Y
>> So, listen everybody. Thank y'all. Love
y'all for the the the the time we get to
spend together with you. Looking forward
to the afterlow today. Make sure you
join us so we can uh talk about the word
of God and how God is going to bless us
uh with the sermons coming up here in a
moment. But uh let's talk about how God
spoke to your heart. Come on to the
afterglow, all of you. And let's just
have a good time in the Lord over there.
Come and do what you what you want to
do. Talk, sing, testify. But anyway, how
about the praise reports, my love?
>> All righty. Well, let me do a few
announcements first.
>> Okay. First up, if you have a prayer
request or a praise report that you
would like to submit or if you would
like to join the prayer team or a
special ops prayer team that is in the
prayer team umbrella, please send an
email to praymanage.urch.
We would love to have you. It's amazing
community and actually special ops teams
are amazing too. Terry and I are in one
in the mornings 7 o'clock a.m. over here
and it has just been a huge blessing. We
are in it with Pastor Ivor and Attante
and Kashif and Pauline and the five of
us pray over
just a lot of things going on. So
>> yes yes yes
>> we have seen answered prayer in real
time. It has been awesome. If you need
that midweek pickup, please join us on
Power Wednesdays every Wednesday at 4:30
p.m. Pacific Standard Time, 6:30
Central, 7:30 Eastern Standard Time.
Following that, we also have the power
line which is live on YouTube and that
is where we do uh live prayer requests
right there on the spot and we will pray
over every prayer that comes in for that
hour.
>> Amen. Amen. The power line's been a lot
of fun uh for a lot of our prayer
warriors and um uh we're we're probably
going to be expanding doing some bigger
things and getting out on some different
platforms. But uh do come and give us
your support on the power line. It's a
beautiful thing and uh uh we have a
great time there. I think last week
sister Shaunene and her mom was there.
So wonderful to see that happening
before that with Joanne and sister
Pauline Shomo Good. always see brother
Danny and sister Jackie there and sister
Angela is such a ball of fire having her
there. Ross and Gina does the power line
along with us and uh next week uh Sister
Ano is Sister Annette I believe will be
doing the power line. So uh
>> Amen.
>> I know she'll be traveling. She's going
to be with family but she will be right
back in on the first of the month. We
we'll probably fill in for them or
Brother Danny and Sister Jackie will
fill in. Somebody will. But the power
line will be going y'all. So come on on
for the live prayer. Look, Amar's going
to do some testimonies, but I just saw
Texas. Sister Gigi just reminded y'all
folks from Texas. Come on and shout it
out on there. And look, Tennessee is
here in the house. I see love, Texas is
here. There's too many of y'all from I
know all the Texas folk getting ready to
jump on the screen, but love y'all from
Texas. God bless y'all and just wanted
to shout y'all out.
>> All right. Almost done with
announcements and then praise reports.
All right. If you would like to join the
women's ministry on Mighty Networks,
please send an email to women
livingmana.urch.
If you would like to join the men's
ministry, please send an email to
menlivingmana.urch.
And did you know that Living Mana has a
Facebook page and we are looking for
engagement and community and people to
just share it? So you can find us on
Facebook at my living mana.
>> Amen. Amen.
>> And that concludes the announcements.
All right. On to praise reports. The
first one coming from Francis Grant.
This was her original prayer request.
Please pray for my husband. He fell last
night and it is painful for him to move.
He will be going to the ER to check for
fractures or breakage.
When she was at the ER, she asked for
prayer for the Lord's intervention. They
are taking X-rays and having to move him
and it is causing excruciating pain.
>> Her update from the hospital. Please
pray for my husband Nigel. He has a
broken hip. He has to have surgery. He
has many health issues to be considered
that can have a directly huge impact on
his ability to go through the surgery
and the recovery. Pray for my strength
in the Lord and her praise report.
Praise God from whom all blessings flow.
I want to thank all the prayer warriors
for their prayers and support. I am so
thankful to say my husband's surgery was
successful. Truly, God's mercy endureth
forever. The surgical team was surprised
to find that his bones were stronger
than they expected for a person his age.
Health conditions and challenges. They
made a point to tell me this after the
surgery. God is marvelous. Thank you
again so much for your prayers and your
help. God bless.
>> From Pauline Goodine. Now, I said
Pauline is in the special ops team that
Terry and I are a part of every morning.
So, this was answered prayer that we
were praying for and it was exciting to
just see the whole thing unfold.
In September, I sat down with my boss to
ask for a raise. The meeting went well
and I was granted a pay raise. Praise
God.
>> Amen. Amen. Last week, I noticed on my
payub that the amount was not what we
agreed upon. Well, family, you already
know what happened. I allowed the enemy
to infiltrate my thoughts. I was
determined to go to my boss and accuse
him of lying to me.
>> Long story short, I went to Jesus and
told him what happened. The Holy Spirit
instructed me to send my boss an email.
I was professional and reminded him
about our conversation and agreement.
Two days went by and I did not hear from
him. I called him on Wednesday evening
and spoke to him about it. He didn't
realize that the pay raise had not gone
into effect. He paid the difference that
I should have received based on my
salary increase. I want to thank God
that he didn't allow me to yield to sin.
My anger could have blocked the very
blessing that God wanted me to have.
Thank you, Jesus.
>> I love you.
>> Amen. Come on, somebody. You know what?
It's all of our, you know, all of us
want to be honest and have to admit that
our first reaction sometimes that
knee-jerk response sometimes is just
like, "Wait a minute. Let me just give
somebody in here a piece of my mind."
>> Well, and then waiting two days. Two
days is a long time to wait. I would be
like,
>> "Yeah, especially when it comes to that
money. Y'all know that money ain't going
to wait no couple days, nothing. You
want to talk about it right now. But
thank God for Sister Pauline and
allowing the spirit of the Lord to
restrain her, allowing her to manifest
the fruit of the spirit in that trying
situation, I'm sure. And we are
rejoicing. Listen, as we got off the
phone call the other day, I I I got to
tell her,
>> okay,
>> I got to Okay,
>> so the yesterday, the Lord told me,
"Call your daughter. She wants to hear
from you." you know, uh we had uh and so
I called her and I mean my daughter, I
mean, such a sweet voice and listening
to her, I get to hear her voice now and
uh we talked and she told me, you know,
she's getting ready to graduate. She
hasn't graduated yet, but she's going to
graduate and already she has been hired
at Providence Hospital in San Pedro. And
I just um
>> he's a proud dad. Hey, look, I could not
I did I couldn't be more proud and and
we had the best conversation we've had
ever. I think
>> it was just amazing. So, thank y'all for
praying for my daughter and myself and
now and we believe in God. Pray pray for
pray for Simon. He's next, my son. So,
thank God. It was beautiful. And thank
y'all. Love y'all so much.
>> Well, I want to share my
>> Oh, Lord have
>> I have a big praise report here.
>> We have a big praise report.
>> We have a big praise report. So, I know
I shared two people's and I wanted to
save mine for last, but
just an overview of this last year has
been very trying for my health. Um, in
the last year, for those who don't know,
I had sepsis four times. Um, when I was
originally diagnosed with a bladder
infection back last December and I had
gotten sepsis, that's what I was being
treated for, which was not the issue all
along. Then I got sepsis again and I
ended up getting referred to a
specialist and ends up I had a kidney
stone that was wreaking havoc on my
body. I actually named my kidney stone
Luther.
So Luther gave me sepsis two more times.
And so I had been in and out of the
hospital all year. Uh hospitalized three
times.
>> Um and it was it was tough. It was
tough. I know some people who have not
survived sepsis one time, let alone
four. Yeah. But I have been feeling so
much better since my last surgery. And I
had a follow-up CT scan and a renal
test. And I just had my doctor's
appointment this week. And I have a
little tiny eeny weeny particle. It's
like 2 millimeters big still left in my
kidney. We're not sure if it's a stone,
a particle, or even like a little tiny
piece of plaque, but the praise report
is I don't have to have surgery again
anytime soon.
>> Um, I feel pretty much back to normal.
Um, I'll have an ultrasound, a followup
in six months and I'm a little deficient
in some things. So, we're going to be
taking care of that to try and prevent
this from happening again. But I just
want to thank everyone for your prayers,
for your generosity, and helping us with
our astronomical medical bills.
>> Amen.
>> And just being there with us through
this year, which has been so rough. And
I know I missed a lot of weekends um
here with you guys because of everything
that I've gone through. But God is good.
He is so good. And we are so blessed and
grateful for bringing us through this
trial. So,
>> amen.
>> There's my long- winded praise report.
>> That's okay. And praise God, you know,
uh we just going to throw that thing in
there and uh and we're going to get
ready to go to the throne of grace, but
we want to say this, you know, it was
December when this thing started,
>> you know, and um I just want to thank
God, you know, especially first lady,
you know, because first lady got on
Ammer real rough, you know, real tough,
you know, in love and that's what got us
motivated to move in in the beginning
and because, you know,
>> I thought I had the flu or some weird
>> virus listen to brother Terry but first
don't play when it comes to stuff like
that, right? So, she she was letting us
know, look, let's go.
>> You need to go to the ER, which was
good.
>> Such a a long drawn out
>> thing. And um
>> you know, we put on a good face, but uh
it there were scary moments, y'all. And
there were scary times and then having
to drive down that road and go to work
and with that on your mind all the time
and all kind of stuff. I thank God for,
you know, the storm showed us something.
It showed us you. Mhm.
>> It showed us your love and it showed us
your prayers. And I want to really shout
out that 24-hour prayer uh ministry, Ros
and Gina, and and Sister Shaun, Sister
Jackie, and Brother Danny, Sister
Annette, and Joanne and all of them. And
Birdie, I love you, Birdie. I know you
were in there praying right along with
us. Uh,
you know, we call her Birdie, but Sister
Birdie is in Jamaica. So beautiful. And
we thank y'all for being on. Sister
Karen, all y'all who were praying so uh
vigilantly and showing us your love and
they somehow were able to see through my
well composed, polished demeanor that I
was troubled, you know, and Pauline and
and and they were just praying and I I
thank y'all for that. Thank y'all. You
know, I put on a good face, but it was
it was rough uh because uh it was my
bride, you know, and uh that that can be
hard. So God God really showed us mercy,
grace, and goodness. And let our
testimony be an encouragement to you.
Let it be an encouragement to you that
God is good. God is good. We don't just
say that thing. And sometimes he put us,
he allows us to find ourselves in these
situations so we can see just how good
he is. Now, you know, like you know, Job
said, "I heard about you. Now I've seen
you for myself." You know, and he
repented in dust and ashes. But thank
God for being so wonderful and so good
in our lives, saints.
>> Amen. My kidneys are back in action.
Everything is good.
>> Yes. Yes. I I thank I am thanking God.
Thanking God. Okay. So, let's go to the
throne of grace. I I have some praise uh
prayer rep requests here and I just want
to keep those. Um I love First Lady's
t-shirt, by the way. Pray, wait, and
trust. God has a plan. Pray, wait, and
trust, y'all. That's a message. That's a
message right there by itself. I want to
thank God for the LC youth. We want to
continue to pray for them. They are
moving up and moving on in the Holy
Ghost, moving in ministry, and we want
to thank God for them. They've done a
wonderful job. We will keep y'all in
prayer. Keep y'all lifted up. I want to
pray for LMOC Global. God has brought us
so far from
>> Pastor and myself. Think about Kung Fu
Theater when we we were thinking about
watching all of the Kung Fu growing up
and imagining we can be those type of
dudes, you know, and we had to move so
we didn't have the language. now
listening this morning, pastor got the
language right along with it. So God has
brought us a long way with Locosc
Global. We're taking the everlasting
gospel around the world. We ought to be
rejoicing saints and continuing to pray
for that. I want to pray God for sister
Curls Woodall and her family. She shared
an amazing testimony today about homing
pigeons and taking that message back
home. He's got one one message in his
mind and that's home. And so I want to
pray for her and her family. Thank her
for being a blessing. Want to pray for
brother Kashif Williams and his family,
his life, his family, his ministry,
everything concerning him. Sister Jamie
has reminded us to pray for those who
are living in daily war zones, whether
it be physical or spiritual. And so,
let's let's keep people in prayer who
are dealing with war. Um, there was that
question on demon possession and general
curses. Pastors are going to be getting
coming back and visiting that again, him
and first lady, next week. I think it's
a deep topic and I think we do need to
get some understanding and clarity and
God's given us that. So, I want to pray
about people who are dealing with that
and need to understand really what's
going on, how to stand up and be
liberated by the truth. I thank the Lord
Jesus who promised us that uh if we
continue in his word, we'll be his
disciples indeed. We will know the truth
and the truth not set us free. The truth
would make us free because we're already
free in Jesus. We just sometime don't
know it. And when the truth show us that
we be then we rejoice. I want to thank
God for my daughter Chavevel. Beautiful.
beautiful, precious girl, young woman
and what God's doing in her life. Um,
one of Charlize Rankin is asking us and
reminding us to remember to pray for
Western Jamaica that they would get up
and get going in the aftermath of the
hurricane. We do pray for Jamaica
continuously and thank God for our
beautiful people there. Brother Taj and
his family and his ministry, reflections
of hope. We've been blessed with by
Brother Taj and his family from the very
start. They are family. We consider them
living men of family. We love you, Taj.
You and and your beautiful bride that
y'all continue on keep on keeping on. Uh
Zadena, we want you having back surgery
on December 8th and we want to keep you
in prayer. We know you already had a
previous surgery that was supposed to be
simple and there's been some
complications and some pain and we know
you want to get up and get moving again
so you can get back to work and and and
and take care of yourself. So, we're
praying for you. Also, those cries that
you have had in your heart, feeling
lonely, feeling a little emotional right
now, it's all right, my sister. We love
you and may God be right there with you.
May God send the miracle you need today.
Might be some companionship, might be
resources, might be whatever. Move in
the name of Jesus. We pray. Precious
father and want to pray for sister
Jackie and brother Danny, their family,
their ministries, re uh with the
Revelation Bible study, their personal
ministry, their family, their home,
their children and grandchildren. Uh
Jackie shared a powerful testimony with
us today, you know, and some other
things that are going on in our family.
So, we want to continue to lift them up
because they are a blessing to us. And
so, we want to do that. Uh, I think it's
SBK. Is it SPK79
or SPK? We want to pray uh about your
cursing and your healing. Now, Amen.
>> You keep coming to this living mana and
getting this word put in. God will do
the rest. You just put the light in. The
darkness will flee. Uh, we want to pray.
Um, you the one that had a surgery that
was supposed to be simple and now you're
getting back to work. It wasn't Zadina.
Oh, Zazena's getting ready to have the
surgery. So, it was you who uh uh had
the surgery and then you're still
dealing with some pain and you're
struggling with that. So, for excuse me
for that confusion. Um and so we we'll
be praying for you, my beloved sister.
Sister Anetta Carr is in the hospital
right now dealing with leukemia. And the
Lanetta, you always send an encouraging
message to us and we we appreciate you.
Please know we're praying for you. God
is more than able to bring you through.
He's there with you. And so uh we will
not stop praying. My beloved sister be
well in Jesus. Sister Gigi says that
she's struggling with her art and public
speaking classes and currently
struggling to know God's will for our
life. And uh we wanted to encourage you.
Sister Gigi, that's a good place to be
in that struggle because some people
just go on with life and don't stop to
ask God nothing. But if you're
struggling to know, then you're a good
place because uh God gonna definitely
bring you where he wants you to be in
time and on time. He's an ontime God,
somebody. Yes, he is. And so we want to
also remember Sister Charaine and her
mother, Sister Dolores, and their
family. They've been a blessing to us.
We pray God bless them and keep them and
continue to raise them up. Now, this was
a name I just I it says Kudak, right?
Washinga.
I think I got it. Kudaka
9969.
You are asking for prayer for revival in
Nambia, South Africa and in Walis Bay. I
pray God move in a mighty way that they
would get up and go out and begin to
share the gospel. Uh my sister, thank
you so much. My brother, thank you for
sharing. Kudak, thank you for sharing
that prayer request. We'll definitely be
praying for revival there. And also, um
Josh Hinsley, our beloved brother in
Ohio, is praying that there will be an
SDA church that will raise up in
MacArthur. And I saw some contact with
someone who's now living I believe in
Arizona that's from also from Ohio. I
pray God will begin to move in some
special way there beyond what we're
asking. And also Charlie Davids 9196 is
praying for the homeless community at
the Adventist outreach program in
central London. We'll be praying that
God will bless and move there in London.
Wow. We are getting an opportunity to
just join hands and join hearts and join
faith with people literally around the
globe. Saints literally when you pray
with us, when you join with us, look
what living mana is doing. This
incredible vision that started as just a
dream in the hearts and minds of pastor
me and sister Atante, even when they
were in the middle of a storm, coming
out of one storm and headed up into a
blessing and from that to another storm
to another. And God has taken this
vision around the globe. Look at what's
happening. Let us continue to pray. And
brother Reed, we're praying for you uh
that you will have the words to speak to
the counselor officer at your wife's uh
visa interview that he would be able to
overcome the uh decision to disqualify
you as her uh visa sponsor. You know,
the Lord says that what God has brought
together, let no man put us under. And
so God move in that interview and and
show him that y'all are one and y'all
are meant to be together because God
brought that together. And God will keep
that together in whatever way he can do
it. Somebody Pastor Enante mentioned a
friend this morning how they thought it
was over. Huh? Say that there ain't no
healing for this one. God is a God of
reconciliation. He can He can bring it
back together. Somebody.
>> Amen.
>> He can do it. He can fix it. Look what
he did with his own bride. He He brought
her back. Came up with a Heaven came up
with a way. Amen. Somebody. Heaven will
always come up with a way. And so let's
go to the throne of grace.
>> Wait.
>> In faith.
>> Hold on.
>> Yes, my love. There was a prayer request
that came in last minute here from Ryu
Guy Reborn.
>> Yes,
>> let me read it out loud before Terry
prays.
>> I would like prayer for this final exam
I took in Greek. I really can't afford
to take the class over again. So, my
prayer is I got the grade I need to pass
so I don't have to retake it again.
>> Brother, you know, I'm glad you stopped
me.
>> Praise God for you, my brother. You're
studying. You're obviously in seminary
there. And so, thank God for you. I'm
I'm I'm knowing that can be that can be
rough, but the Holy Ghost will get
involved with that Greek and open your
mind to it and and give you all you need
with your flash cards and he'll put it
in your heart and mind. You'll start
seeing spiritually those dip thongs
flashing through your mind and
understanding will become clear to you.
So, thank God for you. Thank you for the
prayer requests. We get to join in with
that. And may your ministry uh that God
calls you to be a blessing to many in
Jesus name. And so to the throne of
grace we come precious father in Jesus
mighty and majestic name. Thank you Lord
for the invitation to come. Thank you
for the blood of lamb slain from before
the foundation of the world. Thank you
for the council of peace Lord God where
you entered in and declared before we
even got here Lord God. You'd already
made provision for us Lord God. Thank
you that there's no situation hallelujah
that we can find ourselves in when we're
surrendered to your will. nothing that
you haven't already made provision for.
And so we give you praise today for
that. We give you glory and we give you
honor. Thank you for being our savior,
our conqueror from Calvary, fairest
among 10,000, shelter in a time of
storm, rock in a weary land. Thank you
for being a friend that sticketh closer
than a brother. Oh God, in Jesus name.
Fairest among 10,000. Thank you for
being our shield and exceeding great
reward. Thank you Lord God. Lion of the
tribe of Judah, prince of peace, Lord of
glory, lily of the valley, bright and
morning star, we give you praise, exalt
you today, God, because you are worthy.
You are worthy and we worship you and we
enter into that rest today. Even as we
bring these requests before your
presence today, Lord, we know and
believe, Lord. We have seen and witness
and testify it, God, that you are
greater than all of our trials, greater
than all of our tragedies. I pray that
the faith of someone watching today
would just be elevated through the roof,
God. That someone who had felt like they
couldn't get a hold of you or just could
break through the confusion in their
mind, the cloudiness in their mind and
the darkness. I pray, God, someone
watching Living Mana Online Church
today, someone who will watch Living
Mana Online Church sometime throughout
the week will receive the spiritual
breakthrough that they've been waiting
for. that their eyes would be open, that
their heart would be lifted, Lord God,
and they would be enlightened, that
their shackles and chains would be
broken, that somebody would throw that
dope pipe down, that somebody would put
down the alcohol bottle, that someone
would put their hand over their mouth
getting ready to tell somebody something
they shouldn't, getting ready to say
something they ought not say. I pray in
Jesus' name, God, fill our hearts, God,
with your spirit and with your goodness.
Fill us with your truth and the light of
life, Lord. We thank you today and
praise you for being so wonderful and
good. Thank you for every one of these
prayer requests that we've lifted up
before you. Someone neglected to put
their prayer requests in the chat.
Someone put their prayer requests in the
chat and felt that it was overlooked and
maybe I didn't see it or maybe I didn't
read it here today. But I thank you,
God, that nothing escapes your eyes.
Your word says your eyes run to and fro
throughout the whole earth, showing
yourself perfect on behalf of those
whose hearts are perfect towards you.
show that one today that they're not
overlooked and they're not uh missed,
Lord God, by you, Father, but you're
able, God, and you're good and you're
mindful. And so, we just give you praise
today as we draw near to the throne.
Lord, thank you so much for being so
wonderful and so good and for what
you're doing in and through living
manner and what you will do, what you
have done. God, we praise you. And as we
get ready to receive the word, we want
to thank you, Father, for being so
faithful. Faithful, Lord. We don't want
to take this word for granted. We saw in
that little video not to take anything
for granted. Feed us, oh Lord, with your
word. Lord, enlighten the eyes of our
understanding, God. Show us, Lord God,
what we need to see in this hour to be
what you have called us to be in this
hour, Lord God, in Jesus name. To take
this word to a dying world out there.
And Lord, fill our hearts as we listen
to the pastor proclaim the everlasting
gospel today, the truths of your word
that you've placed on his heart. Fill us
with a love of God. Fill us with a love,
Lord. An uncomfortable love, God. A love
we can't rest, Lord God, until we know
that we're in the center of your will
and that we're showing that love to
somebody around us. Father God, help
this word that comes forth today to take
away some all of us feel these nasty bad
attitudes sometimes, Lord. It just comes
over us, Father. Sin has messed us up,
Lord. But thank you, God, for your
goodness that where sin hath abounded,
grace doth much more abound. In the
mighty and majestic name of Jesus, we
give you glory, honor, and praise. And
so, Lord, thank you for the word that's
about to come forth. Lord, may it be
health to our flesh and and and and and
and and health to our bones and to our
marrow in Jesus glorious name, Father.
And all God's people declare,
>> Amen.
>> Amen. Amen.
I want Jesus.
to walk with me.
I want Jesus
to walk with me
all along
my
primary
journey.
I want Jesus
to walk with me
in my trials.
Lord, walk with me
Don't walk with me
when the shades
of life are
falling.
Yeah.
I want Jesus
to walk with me
in my sorrows.
Lord, walk with me
in my sorrows,
Lord. Walk with me
when my heart is
aching.
I want Jesus
to walk with me.
long.
Walk with me, Lord. Walk with me, Lord.
Walk with me.
Walk with me, Lord. Walk with me.
every day. Lord, I want you to walk.
Walk with me, Lord. Walk with me. Walk
with me.
alone with me.
Welcome, Living Mana Church family. Uh
happy Sabbath to you. Uh I'm glad that
you are tuning in to join in worship
with us today. Uh we are getting ready
to get into the word of God um this
afternoon. and I'm excited about what
the Lord has to share. Uh this message
entitled The Mount of Curses
is uh for me one of my
uh I believe most important messages.
And so I know the title sounds
forboding.
Um but please uh listen to the message
and listen with all your heart and all
your mind and all your soul uh for what
the Lord has to share with us today. Um
please put a one in the chat if you're
ready to get into the word of God. Also,
please if you have not yet subscribed to
Living Mana YouTube channel, please do
that. Uh and share this link. let the
people know that the word of God is
about to be spoken.
And uh with that said, guys, we're going
to go ahead and uh open up with prayer
and begin with this message. Let's do
that now. Heavenly Father, I want to ask
Lord in a in a special way that you
would please speak uh through your word
again, Lord.
Lord, for someone who is struggling
today, I pray that this message will
bring healing, will bring peace,
and will draw us all closer to you,
Lord.
Thank you, Lord, for hearing and
answering because we ask it in Jesus'
name. Amen. Amen.
The mount of curses. The mount of
curses. Um, we are going to take a walk
through the Bible and I'm going to do
this uh in a chronological order. So,
we're going to work our way to the book
of Joshua. But to do that, I want to
trace a series of events that will lead
us up to understanding what we're about
to read, what we will read in the book
of Joshua, particularly Joshua chapter
7. Joshua chapter 7.
So let's begin
with uh Genesis chapter 15 and verse 13.
The Bible says here, God is speaking to
Abraham and he says, the Bible says, he
said unto Abram, "Know of assurityity
that thy seed shall be a stranger in a
land that is not theirs, and shall serve
them, and they shall afflict them 400
years."
The children of Israel
um are prophesied. that it is prophesied
that they're going to spend 400 years in
captivity. So, please put that number in
the chat for me. 400 to represent 400
years of captivity. After that 400 years
of captivity, towards the end of that
400 years of captivity,
God brings a man on the scene by the
name of Moses.
And Moses
um is the is the man that is going to
lead the children of Israel out of
Egypt. And he's going to lead them to
see the promised land. He's going to
lead them to see the promised land. Now
Moses is allowed to see the promised
land, but he is not permitted to
continue on. In Deuteronomy 31 beginning
with verse one, the Bible says, "And
Moses went and spake these words unto
all Israel, he said unto them,"I am 120
years old. I can no more go out or come
in. And al also the Lord has said unto
me, Thou shalt not go over this Jordan.
the Lord thy God, he will go before
thee, and he will destroy the nations
before thee, these nations before thee,
and thou shalt possess them. And Joshua,
he shall go over before thee, as the
Lord has said. So, I want you to note
here that uh Moses is allowed to see the
promised land, but he is not permitted
to continue on. In fact, there is going
to be a transition of power where Joshua
is the one that will lead the children
of Israel
into the promised land. Deuteronomy
31:7, the Bible says, "And Moses called
unto Joshua, and said unto him in the
sight of all Israel, be strong and of
good courage, for thou must go with this
people unto the land which the Lord hath
sworn unto their fathers to give them,
and thou shalt cause them to inherit
it." And the Lord, he is that doth go
before thee, he will be with thee. He
will not fail thee, neither forsake
thee, fear not, neither be dismayed. So
there's a transition of power from Moses
to Joshua.
This transition takes place at the
Jordan. I'm laying the foundation for
you. I want you to understand clearly
the pro the process which we are
following in preparing for what we will
read in Joshua chapter 7. So we're now
in the book of Joshua. And in Joshua
chapter 1, the Bible says, "Now after
the death of Moses, the servant of the
Lord, it came to pass that the Lord
spake unto Joshua, the son of Nun,
Moses, saying, Moses minister, saying,
Moses, my servant, is dead. Now
therefore, arise.
Go over this Jordan, thou and all this
people unto the land which I do give
them, even to the children of Israel.
every place that the sole of your foot
shall tread upon, that have I given unto
you, as I said unto Moses." So, we're
now in Joshua chapter 1. Joshua Moses
has passed the baton to Joshua.
There's a transition of power from Moses
to Joshua at the Jordan. And in Joshua
chapter 3, we'll find that Joshua
crosses the Jordan. And then we get to
Joshua chapter 4. And notice what Joshua
Josh Joshua 4:1 and2 say. It came to
pass when all the people were clean
passed over the Jordan, that the Lord
spake unto Joshua, saying, "Take you 12
men out of the people, out of every man
a tribe,
and command ye them, saying, Take your
hands out of the midst of Jordan, out of
the place where the priest's feet stood
firm, 12 stones, and you shall carry
them over with you, and leave them in
the lodging place where you shall lodge
this night."
In fact, in Joshua 4:14, the Bible says,
"And the Lord the on that day the Lord
magnified Joshua in the sight of all
Israel, and they feared him as they
feared Moses all the days of his life."
Okay. So,
um we are now in Joshua chapter 4. We
started in Genesis uh uh chapter 15
where we found the prophecy of the
children of Israel spending 400 years of
captivity in Egypt. At the end of that
400 years, you have Moses coming on the
scene. Moses is going to lead the
children of Israel to see the promised
land. Moses leads them to the promised
land, but is not allowed to continue
there on. There's a transition of power
from Moses to Joshua. At the Jordan,
Joshua chooses 12 men to take these
stones as memorials.
And then then we get to Joshua chapter
6. In Joshua chapter 6, uh Joshua
chapter 6, the Bible tells us that
Joshua goes to battle against Jericho.
So this is and we know the story.
There's a loud shout. Jericho falls and
the children of Israel defeat Jericho.
That's Joshua chapter 6.
In Joshua chapter 7, Joshua and the
children of Israel are now going to
battle against a place called Ai.
And you know that the first time they go
up against Ai, they lose the battle.
Someone has stolen the Babylonian
garment. They lose the battle. Joshua
cries out to the Lord. They handle their
business. The Lord shows them what
happened. And then in Joshua chapter 8,
they're going to go fight one more time
with Ai. and they will defeat Ai. So
that is a total of three times that
Joshua is engaged in conflict. And that
brings us to Joshua chapter 8. That
brings us to Joshua chapter 8. And now
in Joshua chapter 8, here is what we
read. And earlier I said Joshua chapter
7. I meant Joshua chapter 8. This is the
the the the climax, if you will, of our
what we've been building. We're now in
Joshua chapter 8. And I want you to
notice what the Bible says here.
And all Israel and their elders and
officers and their judges stood on this
side of the ark and on that side before
the priests of Levites which bear the
ark of the covenant of the Lord as well
as a stranger as well as him them that
were born among them. half of them over
against Mount Gerism and half of them
over against Mount Ebal as Moses the
servant of the Lord had commanded before
that they should bless the people of
Israel. And afterward he read all the
words of the law, the blessings and
cursings according to all that is
written in the book of the law. And so
400 years of captivity, Moses leads the
the people to see the promised land. He
sees the promised land, but is not able
to continue on. There's a transition of
power from Joshua, from Moses to Joshua
at the Jordan. Joshua is going to lead
the children of Israel into the promised
land. He chooses the 12 men who take the
12 stones. Uh he goes into battle
against Jericho and then against Ai and
then against Ai again and then he does
something that Moses had commanded him
to do before they had crossed the
Jordan. And that was he was going to
take the 12 tribes of Israel, put half
of them over against Mount Jerisim and
the other half upon Mount Ebal. And he
was to read blessings and curses
on both mountains. Mount Jerisim is
where he would read the blessings and
Mount Ebal is where he would read the
curses. So what I want to do is I want
to go ahead and take a look at the
blessings spoken in Deuteronomy chapter
28. This is where the blessings are
recorded. So let's go to the blessings.
And uh how many of you are ready to hear
the blessings of God? Put a one in the
chat if you want to hear the blessings
of God. And let me ask you a question as
we're preparing to read the blessings.
If God said bless you one time,
if God said blessing to you, just said
to looked at you and said blessed one
time, how many of you would agree that
that would make your entire life worth
living?
If God just said bless to you one time,
I want you to notice Deuteronomy 28:3.
Blessed here, here go the blessings.
Blessed shalt thou be in the field, in
the city, and blessed shalt thou be in
the field. Verse four, blessed shall be
the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of
th of thy ground, and the fruit of thy
cattle,
and the increase of thine kind, and the
flocks of thy sheep. Now, I want you to
understand this, okay? If God says,
"Blessed shalt thou be in the city and
blessed shalt thou be in the field."
That pretty much covers everything.
If you're blessed in the city and you're
blessed in the field, that covers
blessings everywhere. Everywhere you go,
you're going to be blessed. How many of
you would get every anything in the
world to have those two blessings alone?
Just those two blessings. Because,
beloved, those two blessings cover every
possible way you could be blessed. And
yet, God goes on. And listen to what he
says.
Blessed shall be the fruit of thy body,
and the fruit of thy ground, and the
fruit of thy cattle, the increase of
thine kind, and the flocks of thy sheep.
Blessed shalt thy b shall be thy basket
and thy store. Blessed shalt thou be
when thou comest in, and blessed shalt
thou be when thou goest out. The Lord
shall command the blessing upon thee in
thy storehouses, and in all that thou
setth thine hand unto do, and he shall
bless thee in the land which the Lord
thy God giveth thee. Verse 12, the Lord
shall open unto thee his good treasure,
and to and the the heaven to give the
rain unto the land in his season, and to
bless all the work of thine hand, and
thou shalt lend unto many generations,
and shall not borrow. Nine times in all,
put that number in the chat for me,
please. Nine times, God uses the word
blessings for his people. How many of
you would give anything for those nine
blessings?
Deuteronomy 28, the chapter that
contains the blessings from verse one to
verse 12 is all about the blessings.
Amen. Amen. Amen. Amen.
And now, now for the curses.
So, the curses are actually found in the
very same chapter. They're found in
Deuteronomy chapter 28. And the curses
begin
at verse 15. Let's go ahead and read
that. But it shall come to pass that if
if you will not hearken unto the voice
of the Lord your God, to observe to do
all his commandments and his statutes,
which I command thee this day, that all
these curses shall come upon thee and
overtake thee. All these curses. Now,
let's pause for a second.
The curses begin in verse 15.
Deuteronomy 28 has 63
68 verses if I'm correct. 68 verses
altogether.
The rest of the of Deuteronomy 28
is all curses.
Beloved, that is that is over
that is 53,
if I'm counting correctly, 53
verses of curses.
Now, I need y'all to understand the
significance of that.
Um,
if God said to you cursed one time, just
one time, how many of you would pass out
and probably think you'd never wake up
again? Just just if God looked at you
and said one time, you are cursed.
Put a five in the chat if you can relate
with what I'm saying right now.
If God looked at you one time and said
cursed,
that's it. Not even how, just cursed.
How many of you would pass out?
Perhaps all of us. And yet, beloved,
there are 53
verses of curses left in the chapter.
Let's go ahead and look at some of them.
Deuteronomy 28:16 to18. Cursed shalt
thou be in the city and cursed shalt
thou be in the field. So pause for a
second. If you're cursed in the city and
you're cursed in the field, it would
stand to reason that that means you are
cursed in every possible way. Whether
you're in the city or you're in the
field, that should cover everything.
Lord, you don't need to say anymore.
We have the picture. We have it. That's
all you need to say, Lord. You didn't
even It didn't even need to say cursed
in the city or in the field. Just the
fact that God says cursed one time
should be enough
to cause the boldest man
to faint from fear.
And yet, God does not stop at cursed
shall thou be in the city, and cursed
shalt thou be in the field. Let's keep
going.
Cursed shall be thy basket and thy
store. Cursed shall be the fruit of thy
body, and the fruit of thy land, and the
increase of thine kind, and the flocks
of thy sheep. Verse 19, cursed shalt
thou be when thou comest in, and cursed
shalt thou be when thou goest out. Verse
20. The Lord shall send upon thee
cursing, vexation, and rebuke, and all
that thou setest thine hand unto do
until thou be destroyed, and until thou
perisheth quickly, because of the
wickedness of thy doings, whereby thou
hast forsaken me. You would think, you
guys, that this is enough. This is
enough, God. You don't need to say
anymore. And yet, God keeps going. Let's
go to verse 22. I just need you to catch
a get a get a good understanding of the
fact that it seems like God in
Deuteronomy 28 is inventing
ways to curse those who disobey him.
Watch what the go text goes on to say.
The Lord shall smite thee with a
consumption, with fever, and with
inflammation, and with extreme burning,
and with sword, and with blasting, and
with mildew, and shall pursue thee until
thou perish. The Lord shall make the
rain of thy land powder and dust. For he
from heaven shall it come down upon
thee, until thou be destroyed. The Lord
will smite thee with the bot of Egypt,
and with emirates, and with the scab,
with the itch, whereof you cannot be
cured. Thou shalt betroth a wife, and
another man shall lie with her. Thou
shalt build a house, and thou shalt not
dwell therein. Thou shalt plant a
vineyard, and thou shalt not gather the
grapes thereof. Thy sons and thy
daughters, verse 32, shall be given unto
another people, and thine eyes shall
look and fall with longing for them all
the day long, and there shall be no
might in thine hand. Verse 25,
35. The Lord shall smite thee in the
knees and in the legs with a sore botch
that cannot be healed, from the sole of
thy foot unto the top of thy head. Let
me pause for a second. The last time I
preached this sermon, I realized
something. I never saw this before. The
text literally says that the Lord will
come for your knees.
Think about that for a moment.
God literally says, "After all the
cursing that I've that I've done upon
you, I'm coming for your kneecaps.
For your knees. Not even your knees will
be safe." It seems to me that if we are
a people who are just being introduced
to God right now, we must be thinking,
what kind of a God is this?
Why is he tw 14 12 verses of blessings,
53 verses of curses?
How many of you are terrified right now?
Yeah, it's not enough. It's almost like
God wants you to experience some kind of
emotional mental anguish for a reason.
Let's keep going. Verse verse verse 39.
Thou shalt plant vineyards and dress
them, but shall neither drink of the
wine nor gather the grapes, for the
worms shall eat them. Verse 42 and 43.
All thy trees and the fruit of thy land
shall be the lo shall the locust
consume. The stranger that is within thy
gates within thee shall get up above
thee very high and thou shalt come down
very low. Verse 46 and they shall be
upon thee for a sign and for a wonder
and upon thy sea forever. All these
curses.
Verse 52. He shall besiege thee in all
thy gates until thy high fences and
walls come down wherein thou trusted
throughout all thy land. And he shall
besiege thee in all thy gates throughout
all the land which the Lord thy God
giveth thee. It seems like
God is trying to find creative ways to
curse those who do not follow him and
toward her young one that cometh out
from between her feet and toward her
children which shall which she shall be
which she shall bear. For she shall eat
them for want of all things secretly in
the siege and straightness wherein thine
energy shall distress thee in thy gates.
You guys,
this
is mentally overwhelming.
And now that I've taken you through this
journey from Genesis all the way to the
book of Joshua, where Joshua is reading
these blessings and cursings, the
question I have for you is, what do
these mountains mean?
What do these mountains mean?
Put a one in the chat if you're ready.
Put a one in the chat if you're ready to
see the beauty of God's word. I need
y'all to check this out.
Did you know that between the last
prophet of the Old Testament, that's a
book of Malachi, and the New Testament,
there was a period of 400 years. Put
that number in the chat for me, please.
400 years between Malachi
and the New Testament. There's a period
of 400 years
where the children of Israel experience
as it were the absence of God.
At the end of that 400 years,
there is a man who comes on the scene.
This this man's name is John the
Baptist.
In fact, in Malachi 3:1,
Malachi prophesied this man when he
said, "Behold, I will send my messenger,
and he shall prepare the way before me,
and the Lord whom you seek shall
suddenly come to his temple, even the
messenger of the covenant whom you
delight in. Behold, he shall come,
sayith the Lord of hosts." John the
Baptist at the end of 400 years comes on
the scene. And what is his mission? His
mission is to lead the children of
Whereas Moses led the children of Israel
to see the promised man land,
John the Baptist leads the children of
Israel
to the promised man.
Are y'all with me so far?
John the Baptist leads the children of
Israel to see the promised man. Now John
the Baptist in fact in John chapter 1 29
the Bible says in the next day John
seeth Jesus coming unto him saith behold
the lamb of God which taketh away the
sin of the world. Now you'll remember
that when John the Baptist sees Jesus
there is about to be a transition of
power at the Jordan.
John
says in John 3:30, "He must increase,
but I must decrease." There's a
transition of power from John the
Baptist to Jesus at the Jordan, just as
there was a transition of power from
Moses to Joshua at the Jordan. And just
as Moses was not allowed to continue on,
his eyes saw the promised land, but he
could not continue on. So John the
Baptist sees the promised man but he is
not permitted to continue on. Moses
dies, John the Baptist dies.
So you know that it is in Matthew
chapter 3 that we have this transition
of power where the Bible says and Jesus
when he was baptized went straight way
up out of the water and lo the heavens
were open unto him and he saw the spirit
of God descending like a dove and
lighting upon him. In other words,
the voice from heaven saying, "This is
my beloved son in whom I'm well
pleased." Just as Joshua was glorified
that day in the sight of the people, so
Jesus at his baptism at the Jordan where
this transition of power took place, he
was glorified in the eyes of the people.
That's Matthew chapter 3.
You know what happens after Matthew
chapter 3?
In Matthew chapter 4, Jesus, remember
how how Joshua as he's crossing the
Jordan, he is commanded to choose 12
men.
Come on, somebody.
He is commanded to choose 12 men. And I
need you to understand that just as
Joshua did in the Old Testament, Yeshua
does in the New Testament, Jesus does in
the New Testament as he chooses 12 men
that are going to help him accomplish
his mission.
What else happens in Matthew chapter 4?
Matthew chapter 4, you will read these
words. Matthew chapter 4 verse one. Then
was Jesus led up in the spirit of the
spirit into the wilderness to be tempted
of the devil. And you'll remember that
just that Jesus
fought the devil. How many times how
many times did Jesus enter into conflict
with Satan in the wilderness after he
crosses the Jordan?
How many times?
Three times, you guys. How many times
does Joshua go into battle after he
crosses the Jordan, once against
Jericho, twice against Ai three times.
If y'all are with me, if y'all are with
me, please put a one in the chat.
Pastor, we are following you as you're
breaking this down.
So then
in Matthew chapter 4 where we have Jesus
entering into conflict and defeating
Satan three times in a row, we must ask
the question, what happens next? And
what happens next, beloved, is
absolutely mindblowing. See, we're in
Matthew chapter 4 right now. And Matthew
chapter 4 is where the temptations
happen. It's where Jesus begins to
choose his disciples. And then we get to
Matthew chapter 5. And I need to show
you, beloved, how Matthew chapter 5
begins. In fact, we're going to go to
the last verse in Matthew 24. Matthew 4,
I'm sorry, verse 25. Notice what it says
here. And there followed him great
multitudes from the of people from
Galilee and from the capitalists and
from Jerusalem and from Judea and from
beyond the region. So, people are
following him just as the children of
Israel are now following Joshua. Now, I
want you to watch this. Are y'all ready?
I hope you're sitting down. You should
be sitting down
because in Matthew chapter 5,
notice how the chapter begins.
And seeing the multitudes, he that is
Jesus went up into
a mountain.
A mountain.
Jesus seeing the multitude
goes up into a mountain. You remember
that after Joshua defeats Ai, the very
next thing he does is he divides the
people up.
Six on Mount Jerism, six on Mount Ebal.
Six tribes on Mount Jerism, six tribes
on Mount Ebal. And I want you to notice
what the text goes on to say in Matthew
5:1.
And seeing the multitude, he went up
into a mountain where he and when he was
set, his disciples came unto him, and he
opened his mouth and taught them,
saying, "What is that next word?"
Somebody,
somebody help me out.
What is the next word?
That next word, y'all, is the word
blessed.
I'm not making this up.
I'm not. It's right there in the text.
Blessed.
Come on. Let Let's see what he says. So,
blessed are the poor in spirit. All
right. Wow. Blessed are they that mourn.
He says, "Blessed are the meek." He
says, "Blessed are they which do hunger
and thirst after righteousness." He
says, "Blessed are the merciful." He
said, "Blessed are the pure in heart.
Blessed are the peacemakers. Blessed are
they which which are persecuted for
righteousness sake, for theirs is the
kingdom of heaven. Blessed are ye when
men shall revile you and persecute you
and shall say all manner of evil against
you falsely for my sake." Nine times.
Nine times.
Let me rephrase that for you in case you
thought you didn't hear me right. Nine
times the word blessed is used in
Matthew chapter 5 when Jesus is giving
the sermon that we now know as the
sermon on the mount.
Do you remember how many blessings God
spoke back there in Deuteronomy 28?
Let's see if y'all can remember because
I asked you to write the number down.
How many times did God say blessing
blessed in Deuteronomy 28 between verses
1 to 14? How many times? You got it
y'all. Nine times. Nine times.
Nine times. And so now we understand,
beloved, that the sermon on the mount is
a reflection
of Deuteronomy 28 of Joshua chapter 8
where Joshua is speaking the blessings
upon Mount Jerisim.
Wow. If God spoke, if Jesus says to you
blessed in one of the If you fit one of
those blessings, I need you to
understand that you fit all of those
blessings. Because if Jesus says blessed
to you one time, you guys, one time,
then that is everything that we need and
could ever want.
So, so
we got the mount of blessing then. We
get that pastor. But what about this
mount of curses? What is that? And why
was it so? Why is God inventing curses?
I want to show you something.
Let's go to the book of Deuteronomy,
chapter 27. Now, I did not tell you
about this part portion of what was to
happen on Mount Ebal, but now we're
about to find out. It's one chapter
before Deuteronomy 28. And I want you to
notice what the Bible says here in
Deuteronomy 27, beginning with verse 4.
Here's what it says. Therefore, it shall
be when you be gone over the Jordan that
you shall set up these stones which I
command you this day in Mount Ebal.
H that's the mount of curses.
the 12 tribes, the 12 uh uh um uh men
that Joshua chose were to set up these
stones
in Mount Ebal.
And thou shalt plaster them with
plaster, and thou shalt build an altar
unto the Lord thy God, an altar of
stone. Thou shalt not lift up any iron
tool upon them.
And thou shalt build the altar of the
Lord thy God of whole stones, and thou
shalt offer burnt offerings thereof
thereon unto the Lord thy God, and shall
offer peace offerings, and shall eat
there, and rejoice before the Lord thy
God.
Hold on a second.
Um, did we read that right?
Did the text just say that thou shalt
rejoice
before the Lord thy God on Mount Ebal?
How is that even possible? God,
you want us to rejoice on Mount Ebal,
the mountain that you just said, if we
disobey you, all of these curses are
going to be poured upon you. Every one
of them. Not one but all.
How, Lord, can you expect us to rejoice
on this mountain,
the mount of curses?
Let me tell you, beloved. Let me tell
you the amazing, mindblowing,
mindaltering
truth of why God said, "Rejoice on Mount
Ebal." You want to know why? Let me say
it this way. It's as if God was saying,
"If you disobey me, I am going to curse
you in a billion different ways. I am
going to curse you. I am going to to
fill a cup full of curses that you are
going to have to drink.
And now
build an altar
on this mountain.
Build an altar on this mountain.
Not on Mount Ebal. Build an altar on not
on Mount Jerism. Build an altar on Mount
Ebal and sacrifice
sacrifice an animal on that mountain.
Wow.
Wow. Could it be, beloved, that the
reason we are called to rejoice at Mount
Ebal is because the curses that were
supposed to be poured out upon us
would be poured out upon one who would
be sacrificed in our place.
Wow.
Wow. So you mean all this time that you
were trying to get this mental anguish
in our mind of wait a minute what what
if if I don't obey you what's going to
happen to me? What? That and all this
mental anguish you are trying to get us
to understand and experience was to give
us an idea,
a small fraction of an idea
of what Jesus
would go through
on our behalf.
Come on, let me show you. Let me show
you. In Matthew 26:36,
the Bible says, "Then cometh Jesus with
them unto a place called Gethsemane."
And he said unto his disciples, "Sit ye
here while I go and pray yonder." And he
took with him Peter and the two sons of
Zebedee, and began to be sorrowful
and heavy.
Then saith he unto them, "My soul is
exceeding sorrowful, even unto death.
Watch. Try ye here and watch with me.
Watch with me. Watch with me. Watch
with me.
Why?
Why? Listen to what he says. And he went
a little further and fell on his face
and prayed, saying, "Oh my father, if it
be possible, let this cup pass from me.
Nevertheless, not as I will, but as thou
wilt." And he cometh unto his disciples,
and find them asleep, and saith unto
Peter, What could you not watch with me
one hour? Watch and pray that you enter
not into into temptation. The spirit is
willing, but the flesh is weak. And he
went away again the second time and
prayed, saying, "Oh my father, if this
cup may not pass from me except I drink
it, thy will be done." Here's what I
need y'all to understand, beloved. If
you want to know what was in the cup,
if you want to know why it was that
Jesus trembled,
now
you have a fraction of an idea because I
need you to understand that words cannot
there are no words to explain pain the
anguish that Jesus went through. But
Deuteronomy 28
15-68
give us a smidg of an idea.
Picture yourself standing there at Mount
Ebal and Joshua is reading these curses
to you and you are literally cowering
before God. You're thinking, "This God
is a is a tyrant. This God is mean. This
God is vindictive. This God is exacting.
Imagine all those feelings you're having
in your heart. And it's as if God is
saying, "I know what you think about me.
I know what you will think about me.
But I need to show you the depth of my
love for you.
I need to show you that I was willing to
drink those 53
verses of curses. Though you deserved
it, I took it in your place.
I need you to just pause and meditate on
that for a moment.
The Bible says in Isaiah 53:1 and 2,
"Who has believed our report? And to
whom is the arm of the Lord revealed?
For he shall grow up before him as a
tender plant and as a root out of dry
ground. He has no form nor nor
comeliness. And when we shall see him,
there is no beauty that we should desire
him. He is despised and rejected of men.
A man of sorrows, acquainted with grief,
and we hid as it were our faces from
him. He was despised and we esteemed him
not. Surely he has borne our griefs and
carried our sorrows. Yet we did esteem
him stricken, smitten of God and
afflicted. But he was wounded for our
transgressions. He was bruised for our
iniquities. And the chastisement of our
peace was upon him. With his stripes we
are healed. We like sheep have gone
astray. We have turned everyone to his
own way. And the Lord has laid on him
the iniquity of us all. Beloved,
if you want to know what was in the cup
that Jesus drank on our behalf,
you now know it.
You now know it.
And beloved, you know it. Not even
experientially.
You know it just by the fear it invoked
in you. Put a one in the chat if if as I
was reading these curses, you were like
God, really?
Like, is sin that deep to you?
Is disobeying you that deep to you that
that you would put all these curses upon
us?
Beloved, it's as if God is trying to
show us just how dangerous sin is.
And then as that sin bullet is coming
towards you, he pushes you out of the
way and stands in your place. The bullet
that your sin set in action.
You deserved that bullet. We deserved
that bullet.
And Jesus pushed it. The cross pushed
you out of the way.
Pushed you out of the way
and delivered you
from death.
You guys, I'm gonna I'm gonna do
something that that I have not done
before.
I I have half a sermon left to preach,
but I feel like I need to stop right
here.
There's more that that that can go to
this. And we kind of begin to go in a
different direction, but
I need to stop right here. And beloved,
I think
I think this is a place that we need to
just reflect
and meditate
on what Jesus did for us.
When the Bible says, "For God so loved
the world that he gave his only begotten
son," we don't understand the gravity of
that.
We don't understand the gravity of what
Jesus took upon us. And I can I can
assure you this. When the Bible says we
love him because he first loved us, I
genuinely believe that it is not until
we understand
just how much Jesus suffered for us
that we can truly begin to appreciate
and to understand the kind of love
that this type of sacrifice requires.
demands
anything less than the ultimate love
of this for this sacrifice is unworthy
of the sacrifice. Do y'all get what I
just said? If if you walk away from this
and are like, "Oh man, wasn't that
sweet?" You don't understand.
You don't understand. If you walk away
from this and you're like, you know,
man, that that was a pretty that's a
pretty deep love. You don't understand.
I think the only way
that you can actually fully understand
is if you are left speechless.
If you are left speechless. If
if you are saying to yourself there is
no way and it's not something we can
fake. It's not when you when you come to
the place where you're like how do you
Yeah. How do you explore the depth or
the the height or the breadth
of what we just heard? How do you do
that?
When you're left speechless, you're in
the right place.
And it's not to say that there aren't
words to kind of help convey
some of what you understand about this
sacrifice.
But beloved, I need you to understand.
Maybe this is something the disciples
understood that many of us don't. Maybe
this is the reason why they were willing
to die the way that they died. Why they
were willing to suffer the way that they
suffered. Could it be that when you
understand the depth of the cross?
When you understand the depth of the
cross,
could it be?
Could it be
that the cross was designed to leave us
speechless?
Maybe that ought to be the name of the
sermon. Speechless.
Speeus might be that sign
that says, "Yeah, you get it. I get it
now."
And while I can use words,
words fall short
of what Jesus did for us at the cross.
I want to I'm I'm I'm going to
transition in my sermon and I and I'm
and I'm going to show you this same
thing from another perspective that I
need you to understand and I'm just
going to kind of freestyle the the No,
no, no. I'm not going to let Let me I
think I am going to freestyle the rest
of this. Okay. Uh slide team, forgive me
for not using the rest of the slides. Um
but you know, I don't do this often,
right? So I know you understand
what Jesus did at the cross
defeated death.
What Jesus did at the cross defeated
death. It defeated sin. And what I want
you to understand is that
the evidence of this
is when the stone
was rolled away
from the tomb of Jesus.
The stone is rolled away from the tomb
of Jesus
by an angel.
and and an angel is seen sitting on the
stone. And I love that imagery of of of
an angel sitting on the stone because
what I want you to understand, beloved,
is that the stone would have been there
was a seal on the stone. Y'all remember
that? And that seal on the stone would
have been the seal of Satan's power. And
you understand that a seal is designed
to to to not be tampered with. Do not
break. Do not tamp. That's what a seal
represents. do not tamper with.
A seal means something is unchangeable.
And the fact that an angel rolls away
the stone that had the Roman seal on it
and the angel is sitting on the stone.
I used to share this story often when I
was growing up. My older brother, my my
older brother who is uh uh my older
brother, not my youngest, but my older
brother who was who is I always felt he
was 69. I felt he was 69 from from the
day he was born. like I've just always
known him to be like super tall and
super big. And when I was around 12 or
13 years old, I remember, you know,
growing up, I remember he's 5 years
older than me and I remember getting
into fights with my brother and I would
be so mad. I'd be like, I am going to
beat you down and he would just be
laughing at me. He'd be holding my my my
head with his hand while I'm swinging
and crying and and you know, as brothers
do. and we'd just be fighting and you
know I would be fighting and he'd be
laughing and when he got tired of me
trying to fight him he would just pick
me up, put me on the ground and sit on
me. There was nothing more humiliating
in my experience of fighting my older
brother than him sitting on me and
laughing laughing while I'm there
crying. Do y'all understand the imagery
of an angel sitting on the stone that is
sealed saying do not tamper with
Jesus
through his death. Jesus through what he
drank on our behalf
has shown the way out of death and out
of the tomb.
Do y'all understand what I'm saying?
We love him because he first loved us.
He died for us.
He opened the grave for us. And and
here's what I want y'all to get,
beloved. Because remember that story
where where um where uh Lazarus has been
dead and he's dead for 4 days and and
Jesus waits he waits
for Lazarus to die and then four days
later he ends up at the tomb and when he
ends up at the tomb and he says remember
what he says he says roll away the
stone. Here's what I need y'all to get
beloved.
Jesus drank that cup
in order
to roll away the stone.
The stone that says there's no hope for
you. The stone that says you will surely
die. The stone that says uh uh you have
no no there's there's no no future for
you. The stone that says you are in
bondage. Jesus drank the cup
to provide a way out of death.
So when he says to to to the to the
people, "Roll away the stone." And and
they reply to him, one of the sisters
reply to him, "Jesus, he's been in the
tomb for four days. He stinkketh.
He stinkketh." That's what the text
says. "He stinkketh."
I got a question for you.
He's been in the tomb four days. He's
stinking.
My husband
hasn't been following you, Lord, for the
last 15 years. He stinkketh.
Lord, I've been I've been
I've been away from you for the last 20
years. I stink it.
My son, my daughter, they're not
following you. They stink. How can you
bring this person back to life? And God
says, "Listen, I need you to understand.
I drank
of that cup
to have the right as your representative
to set you free. So it doesn't matter
how much you stink.
It doesn't matter how much you stink.
Jesus says,
"I've come to roll away the stone. I
have that right. I have that authority.
I have that power.
And I need you to understand how how how
how how
willing I was to roll away your stone. I
had to drink the cup to do it.
I had to drink the cup to do it.
You may be thinking to yourself today,
you know what? I stink.
I stink.
I know I stink.
You might be thinking that about your
your children, about your your spouse,
about people you want to be. Look, this
person,
they don't know you.
They don't know you. They've been out of
the church. My son fell away from the
church for for for 10 years. He
stinkketh by now. Lord, is it can you
can you actually say roll away the
stone? I want you to understand that
Jesus
died.
Not just any death, you guys.
He died. He drank of that cup.
He took the curse upon himself
in order that he might set us free
from our tombs.
Set us free from our bondage.
Set us free
from sin and death.
And I need you to consider this.
It is when we have when we understand
that love,
it then becomes
impossible
for us to hate other people,
to be angry with other people. You want
to know why Paul could almost be killed
by a crowd of people and then come to
and try to get back to preach to them
again? You want to know why Paul could
do that?
I believe it's because he saw that love.
He saw that love.
When you see what was in the cup,
when you see what was in the cup and you
see Jesus willingly drinking that cup on
our behalf,
how can you hate? How can you despise
other people? How can you hate people
who are Muslim
or fascist
or whatever label you want to put on
them? How can you hate? You might hate
the smell. I get that. He stinkketh.
That's purely reasonable.
But God's love
doesn't care about he's thinking.
We might be like, "Man, I'm holding my
nose." But God is like, "Bring me to
that person. I want to bring that person
to life.
I want to bring that person to life."
So, here's my appeal.
My appeal
is for those of you that are that are
I'm hoping
speechless right now.
I'm hoping speechless,
emotionally speechless. You may be
speaking with him. You may be like,
"Man, this is I've never seen it this
way before."
But you've hit that emotional
speechless
state
and you're saying and you're saying to
yourself, Lord, I need to I need to I
need to
dwell in this.
Lord, help me to meditate.
Help me to meditate on the sacrifice
in a deeper way than I have ever before.
Because I am convinced that if I can
understand and truly understand the
depth of the cross,
it will change everything about me.
I will cease to stink.
I will help others by the grace of God
to cease to stink
because when I show them what you did
for them,
Lord, help me. help me to marinate.
Like I mean, who would have ever thought
y'all that reading 53 verses of curses
could produce such love in the heart,
such speechlessness,
and you're saying today, "All right,
Lord,
I
forgive me for taking the cross so
lightly. Forgive me for taking the cross
so flippantly. Forgive me for failing to
understand the mental anguish that Jesus
really went through. For the first time
in my life, after reading Deuteronomy
28, I now get a glimpse of what he
actually suffered mentally on my behalf.
And Lord, this changes everything.
This changes everything.
Lord,
help me to take that love in and for
that love to be the love that I have in
my heart towards you and towards others.
That's the appeal. I'm simply asking for
a one in the chat. That's the appeal.
Lord,
grant me
that kind of love.
Grant me that kind of love.
That's your desire. Put that one in the
chat.
Put that one in the chat as we close in
and pray. Heavenly Father,
Lord, I I realize that uh I didn't
finish half the sermon today. There's
other half of the sermon I I didn't even
touch.
Um
but Lord, I felt moved
to just stay right there and to build on
that right there.
So Lord,
please
move upon your people.
move upon your people that we may
understand
the depth of the love
that you have for the world.
This is not even just for your people.
It's for the world. You so loved not the
church. You so loved the world.
That stands for every person who has
ever lived.
That your son was willing to take that
cup upon himself, the cup that belonged
to us.
Lord, plant this love in our heart
and may it transform us. May it convert
us. May it fill us
with the love
that is demanded of this kind of
sacrifice.
Let this not be Lord a surface love
but Lord let that love be as deep as the
cup.
Thank you Lord.
Thank you for hearing and answering our
prayer because we ask it in the name of
Jesus. Amen. And amen.
We're going to go ahead and put the uh
link for the afterglow in the chat. And
um
please again feel free to to uh join us
in that afterlow discussion. Um may God
continue to bless you. May God draw you
close to him. May God set your heart on
fire. May God fill you with the love
that Jesus has for us.
Amen.
God bless you. Let me go ahead and share
um just our closing uh slide that if you
would like to um
uh to follow uh living mana um you can
click on any or you can scan any one of
these um
uh QR codes.
Uh so you'll see there connect with
LMOC, you'll see the prayer requests. Um
if you're interested in Bible study, and
if you want to follow us on social
media, those are the QR codes, the email
addresses. And again, may God bless you
and keep you. Um amen.
Thank you for joining us today. If this
is your first time worshiping with us,
please check out our website at
livingmana.urch.
We are not just here for Sabbath
service. We have weekly programming too
that covers mental health, physical
health, weekly prayer service, financial
health, and proving the existence of
God. It is our desire that our
programming will continue to bless you.
Please continue to pray for us as we
fulfill God's mission to go into all the
world with the gospel of Jesus Christ.